Chapter 2
Memory transcription subject: Governor Tarva of the Venlil Republic

Governor Tarva,
Leader of the Venlil Republic

Date [standardized human time]:
July 12, 2136

A shiver crept down my spine, and it wasn’t only because of the frosty air. The thought of standing in close proximity to a predator made my skin crawl, but it was too late to turn back now. All I could do was watch, with mute horror, as the human ship powered down, and a landing ramp unfurled. The primates marched onto Venlil soil, and I suppressed a whimper. This felt like a nightmare I would wake up from at any moment.

Noah and Sara marveled at their surroundings with wide-eyed fascination. Their gaze lingered on the intricate mansion behind them, then shifted to the city silhouette in the distance. The way they physically rotated their head to look around was uncanny. The menacing eyes of a predator didn’t quite offer the peripheral vision we enjoyed, that much was clear.

There was no way they were appreciating the beauty of our architecture. An ominous thought crept into my mind; were they only landing to scout an invasion?

Noah’s eyes landed on our diplomatic envoy, and he stalked toward us without further hesitation. There were a mere three individuals present: me, Kam, and my diplomatic advisor, Cheln. I knew it was a pitiful showing, but it had been next to impossible to persuade anyone to tag along.

“Listen,” I hissed. “We need to act normally. No fear, and no emotion.”

Kam flicked his ears in disgust. “I can’t believe you invited them here.”

“We are buying time for the Federation to arrive.”

“But how can you even look at them? You want to speak to those…creatures, for hours?”

“Of course not. But the other option is another war with predators, and we see how well that’s worked out with the Arxur. If there is a slight chance to avoid bloodshed, I will take it. Happily.”

“We should’ve blasted that ship out of the sky, while we had the chance. If you expect me to welcome these humans with open arms, that’s not going to happen.”

“You are not to antagonize them. Are we clear?” I growled.

Kam huffed, and I feared that was an answer of itself. There was no time to persuade him though, as the two humans had closed within earshot. I prayed that the advisor would come to his senses, and keep his thoughts to himself. We needed to put our best foot forward, if we wanted to get rid of the beasts peacefully.

Keeping up the appearance of strength was important, if only to discourage the humans from decimating our home. Trying to rile them up was a different story; that was nigh suicidal. Predators thrived on the assertion of dominance, so I doubted they’d turn down a blatant challenge.

“Governor Tarva.” Noah stopped a few paces away from our group, and flashed his teeth. “It’s lovely to meet you in person.”

My heart pounded, fear coursing through my veins like a dreadful cocktail. There was not a worse visual cue in the galaxy than flaunting one’s fangs. The threat it communicated felt much more tangible in person. I swayed on my feet, trying to fight off the light-headedness.

A thud sounded beside me, which I realized was Cheln hitting the pavement. My diplomatic advisor fainting was not a good look, I knew that. Even Kam had his ears pressed against his head, earlier bluster forgotten.

Wonderful, I thought. So much for behaving normally.

Noah’s eyes stretched wide, and his mistake seemed to dawn on him. He quickly covered his mouth with a hand.

“Um, sorry,” the predator captain muttered. “I didn’t mean to startle you. Are they ok?”

There was no way to salvage the optics of this one; the humans definitely realized we were afraid of them at this point. I don’t think my plan could have collapsed in a more disastrous manner. The initial idea of surrendering crept back into my mind. Whatever their ulterior motives were, there was nothing to deter them from taking what they pleased.

The strange thing was, Noah seemed more distraught than amused. This species was slower to pounce on weakness than the Arxur. Perhaps there was still a chance to salvage the meeting, or explain away the behavior?

I flicked my ears, trying to calm myself. “Yes, he’ll be fine. This is just—a bit overwhelming.”

“Aliens landing on your planet. That must come as a terrible shock.” Sara exhaled heavily, before scribbling something on her notepad. “You’re handling this quite well, all things considered.”

“I can’t imagine what this would be like without your translator,” Noah said. “Please, forgive us. We’re new to this whole first contact business.”

Kam knelt by Cheln’s side, trying to rouse him. Given that the nurturing trait stemmed from compassion, that wasn’t the sort of behavior to exhibit in front of predators either. I had to nip this conduct in the bud, or else the primates would think it was commonplace. That answered what I should do, but how could I leave a man to die in the cold? How could I chastise my military advisor for basic empathy? That level of cruelty was beyond my sensibilities.

Noah stooped beside the fallen diplomat, and I braced myself for the worst. Predators placed no value on sentient life, not even their own; the Arxur taught us that much. It was obvious the human thought we should abandon Cheln, rather than allow weakness to tarnish the gene pool.

“How can I help?” were the only words that came out of his mouth.

I gaped at the human in disbelief, certain I had misheard. Where were the derisive comments, making light of Cheln’s condition?

“You’ve helped enough,” Kam spat.

Noah lowered his head. “I’m sorry. It was an accident.”

“It’s alright,” I jumped in, before a quarrel could break out. “I apologize for my advisor’s behavior. He’s a bit…on edge.”

“I understand,” the male human said, with a despondent sigh. “I fear I’ve ruined this whole thing.”

“Noah meant no harm.” Sara patted her companion on the back reassuringly. “Seeing an alien culture firsthand…it’s the opportunity of a lifetime. You have no idea how excited we are. Clearly, that wasn’t expressed in the best way.”

The humans’ behavior was growing more baffling by the minute. Everything in the Federation’s database suggested this was a base, violent species. I thought they wouldn’t be able to turn their weapons against us fast enough. While their visual cues aligned with that assumption, their temperament seemed otherwise mellow.

Why maintain this ruse? If they were probing for weakness, as I hypothesized, they had already seen enough to arrive at a conclusion on that front. I was beginning to think I didn’t understand their intentions at all.

Perhaps these predators were capable of higher brain functions than we gave them credit for.

“Can you help us carry Cheln inside?” I took a deep breath, waiting for my translator to catch up. “We’ll give you a tour after that.”

The humans nodded, and positioned themselves to shoulder the brunt of the weight. A faint hope stirred in my chest. They were in no rush to finish us off! That meant we had time to wait for the cavalry after all.

I knew the Federation’s response would be harsh, when they found predators traipsing about the Venlil homeworld. Their actions would be along the lines of Kam’s suggestions: shoot first, ask questions later. The only reason this particular species hadn’t been wiped out, was we believed them to be extinct already. But the plans to obliterate Earth were drafted centuries ago. Eradicating humanity, in one fell swoop, might still be possible.

We only needed to stall the landing party a little longer. What would happen to Noah and Sara next…well, an attempt would be made to capture them for scientific study. If the task proved too difficult, a special ops team would be sent to dispatch them.

A strange guilt tore through my stomach, at the thought of the humans tied up in a lab. It was a misguided sense of empathy, but...

They are predators! They survive by killing species lower on the totem pole. They literally eat flesh, I scolded myself. These humans slaughter each other, all the time, anyways.

“Thanks for your hospitality, Governor.” Sara cleared her throat, locking eyes with me. “I can tell our species will be great friends, one day.”

The mere sight of these creatures disgusted me, but what if we were wrong about them? Wasn’t my intention to avoid bloodshed?

“Yes…friends.” I flicked my ears in agreement, and tried to bury my conscience. “I hope we will be.”

⋯ ✧ ⋯ ✧ ⋯

Chapter 3
Memory transcription subject: Governor Tarva of the Venlil Republic

Governor Tarva,
Leader of the Venlil Republic

Date [standardized human time]:
July 12, 2136

The tour of the governor’s mansion started off without incident, and my nerves began to settle down. The humans tailed behind Kam and I, with questions pertaining to every subject under the sun. Culture, history, politics: they couldn’t absorb information fast enough. Had any other species arrived at our doorstep, with such childlike curiosity, their enthusiasm would be lauded.

Hell, if you didn’t look at the humans, you could almost forget they were predators.

My brain switched into autopilot mode, as I steered our group to the next stop: my office. However, the second I opened the door, I realized I had made a dreadful mistake. In this morning’s panic, I had left a TV on. The news was cycling through footage of bomb shelters across the planet. Government advisories played on loop in the background. They were speaking rather candidly about the humans’ foray, and the likelihood of mass casualties.

I scrambled to turn it off, but it was too late. The humans wandered over to the screen, staring in silence. They hadn’t been this quiet since we started the tour. Seeing masses of people, huddled together, crying, must have stirred something in them.

“I was wondering why there were so few staff here. No reporters either,” Noah said finally. “They’ve all been evacuated, haven’t they?”

I cast my gaze downward. “Yes.”

“You thought we were here to attack you.” There was a flash of something in his brown eyes, and he pressed a hand to his forehead. “My God…Sara, you see how they look at us. I think they still believe that.”

“Is that true, Tarva?” Sara asked. “What do you think is our purpose?”

Panic fluttered in my chest. There was no way to formulate a convincing reply. I took a few steps back, eyeing the humans warily. To deny the accusation would be to discount their intelligence; they would see right through any further deception. Silence was a way of confirming their suspicions, without having to vocalize our terror.

Kam, however, was eager to supply the answer. “To kill us. And to have a grand old time dragging it out.”

“No, no, no! That is not the case at all,” Noah hissed. “We mean you no harm. Look, if you want us to leave, we will.”

Sara raised her hands slowly. “We never wanted to cause fear, or disrupt your lives. We just wanted to meet other people…other people like us…”

“There are no people like you,” Kam growled.

“Really?” She pointed to a 3D photo on my desk, a hard glint in her eyes. “What about them?”

The picture in question was of myself, at a conference with dozens of Federation leaders. It was obvious, to any intelligent observer, that those diverse lifeforms were not of Venlil origin. What were the humans supposed to think? Seeing us comfortable with other aliens, they had to be wondering why they were so feared. I cursed myself for such a blatant oversight.

“You’re right.” I managed to speak, though my voice was hardly more than a whisper. “They’re not from this world. Like you.”

Noah cleared his throat. “How many intelligent species are there…that you know of? How did you find each other?”

I hesitated. If the humans intended to purge the galaxy, news of the Federation’s existence would give them a starting point. It might also tip them off to the coming rescue party, and cause them to accelerate invasion plans. But by the same token, they would discover it anyways. At least this way, we could gauge their reaction.

“Hundreds. Most of us are members of the Galactic Federation. It’s a central governing body of sorts.”

“Why do we bother you then? You’re used to aliens.” Sara’s eyes narrowed to unnerving slits. “Do we resemble something from your past?”

A growl rumbled in Kam’s throat. “You’re a predator. A sentient predator.”

Wonderful. Could this conversation have gone any worse? In his hatred, the military advisor had just told the humans the actual reason they were different. It stood to reason that if they were predators…by default, we were the opposite. If their instincts weren’t awakened before, they had to be salivating now.

There was a long silence, and I could almost see the gears turning in Sara’s mind. Surprise flashed on her face, as though she didn’t understand why their nature mattered. Was this the first time the notion crossed her mind? It was tough to believe the humans were that oblivious to the food-chain dynamics.

“Is that uncommon?” she asked.

“Very.”

“How many are there?”

“You’re the second.”

Noah turned his piercing gaze toward Kam. “Who is the first?”

Silence blanketed the room with a heavy grip. Nobody wanted to explain what happened with the Arxur; not even Kam would offer pointed comments on that subject. We didn’t need to give the humans any ideas. The captain seemed to notice our expressions darken, and the lines on his own face hardened.

“Who is the first?” he repeated.

What words could provide an adequate description of evil incarnate? My eyes swelled with water as memories resurfaced. My father, captured alive on the warfront, shipped back piece by piece. The day the Arxur launched a gas attack against my daughter’s school and left her braindead. The slave pens, the irradiated worlds, the Venlil kept as cattle…

I buried my head in my paws, trying to hide the tears. Showing such weakness in front of the humans was the worst thing I could do. This species, for all its refined words, was cut from the same cloth as our oppressors. If they saw the extent of our pain, it would be weaponized down the road.

Noah’s eyes widened, and my heart sank in my chest. The observant visitor had noticed my emotional lapse, and seemed to be debating his next action. After a moment’s thought, he shuffled closer to me. Every instinct screamed at me to back away, but my paws refused to budge.

As the predator reached out with a meaty paw, I waited for him to strike me. My mind was braced for taunting, torture, or whatever else may come.

Instead, he gently placed an appendage on my shoulder. “Whatever they did, we’re not like that. We’re not going to hurt you, okay?”

Something seemed to snap in my soul, like a series of cracks spreading through a dam. Raw emotion poured through my psyche, and I broke down, sobbing uncontrollably. Noah pulled me closer to him, stroking my head in a soothing manner. His embrace was warm, soft, and delicate, yet I could feel the strength in his arms. There was a silent promise of safety in his grasp. He released me after a few seconds, and wiped a tear off of my face.

Kam’s jaw looked like it was about to fall off. It was rare to see the general left speechless, but I understood why. Kindness was antithetical to the nature of a predator; he couldn’t believe his eyes.

For the first time since the humans appeared, I considered that they might be benevolent. They had to feel empathy to understand how to comfort someone, after all. A decision cemented itself in my mind. I couldn’t allow innocent people to die, simply because of their appearance. The predators might be a threat, but we had judged them based on preconceived notions.

“I believe you, Noah,” I sniffled. “I’m sorry.”

“That’s the first time you’ve said my name!” The human turned his head away, hiding a ‘smile.’ “Either of our names.”

I chuckled. “B-better late than never. Kam, rescind the planetary distress signal.”

“I can’t do that, ma’am,” the advisor said.

“I wasn’t asking your opinion. That was an order!” I snapped. “For stars’ sake, I’ll do it myself.”

“You don’t understand. The Federation is already here. They’re hailing us now.”

A string of curses escaped my lips, and the humans tilted their heads in confusion. I tried to imagine how the poor saps felt. A few hours ago, they hadn’t even known extraterrestrial life existed. Now, they learned of a galactic community; one that hated them without provocation. They were taking the news in stride, but it had to be overwhelming.

Unfortunately, I still had one more bombshell to drop on them. How terrifying would it be, as guests on another world, to have warships arrive hellbent on killing you?

“Wait, why is that bad?” Noah asked. “I thought the Federation are your friends.”

I avoided his gaze. “They came because we set off a distress signal. They’re expecting a fight.”

“I see. Well, why don’t we talk to them, and explain that it was a misunderstanding? Once they know that we’re peaceful–”

“No. I appreciate the thought, but the second they see your…” I waved a paw in the general vicinity of my mouth and eyes. “They won’t listen to a word you say. They’ll want you dead.”

Or worse, I added to myself.

“Right…” the human muttered. “So…”

“I’m sorry about all this, really.” I scratched my chin, trying to think. “I’ll try to drive them off. Just stay out of sight, and let me do the talking. Okay?”

Noah nodded. “Got it.”

I took a deep breath. Despite their repulsive appearance, the humans’ actions exuded such a genuine kindness. They were strangely charming, when you sensed the person beneath the monster. If anything happened to Noah and Sara, the responsibility fell on my shoulders. To think minutes ago, I had been hoping for the Federation to swoop in and save us.

Now, my only objective was to save the lives of two predators.

⋯ ✧ ⋯ ✧ ⋯

Chapter 29
Memory transcription subject:

Captain Sovlin,
Federation Fleet Command

Date [standardized human time]:
October 3, 2136

Our van cruised along the multi-lane highway, granting me a perfect view of the passing scenery. The road was packed with cars, with light signals governing the traffic flow. The humans were more enterprising and entertainment-driven than I anticipated. Intermittent signs advertised shops, restaurants and hangouts. Dwellings were mostly tucked away on side streets, away from the hustle-and-bustle of traffic.

Earth is not as harrowing as I expected. There’s not a single sign of violence or corpses lying around. It’s just people, going about their lives.

We were en route to a refugee camp, per the Terran government’s request. Despite their best efforts, humans lacked knowledge of our basic biology and necessities. They also were having difficulty getting any Gojids to speak to them…for obvious reasons.

The predators asked whether I would be willing to provide guidance, and assist communication with the more frightened individuals. My attorney noted that there was nothing offered in return, but I was happy to help my people. The few thousand that were left, anyways.

Anton leaned in. “Remember, this is a test to see if you’ll cooperate. You need all the goodwill you can get here. Don’t do anything stupid.”

The lawyer looked nervous sitting next to me, even with the cuffs around my forepaws. An ankle monitor was also strapped to one leg, suppressing my circulation. The predators didn’t trust me not to run off, the second I tasted fresh air. If I intended to flee, why would I have flown a ship into the heart of their territory?

There were two UN officers at the front of the vehicle, wearing matching artificial pelts. The primates’ skin must be sensitive to light, with how they wore extensive garments at all times. Their eyes barely left me; the constant tracking meant my spines hadn’t settled for the hours-long ride. The build-up of fear chemicals was dizzying.

I coughed. “Uh, guard predators. C-can…I say something, if I, um…think that my people are b-being mistreated?”

One of the officers, named Samantha, gave a curt nod. “Yes. You may.”

“If you have any ideas for cultural elements that are missing, that’s acceptable as well,” the other soldier, Carlos, growled. “We know nothing of your religions or customs.”

That old anxious habit of chewing at my claws cropped up again. The most popular deity worshipped in our systems was the Great Protector, a nature spirit that warded off predators. I never believed in such nonsense myself; judging by how the Arxur terrorized us, there was no one safeguarding our cradle.

Probably shouldn’t tell literal predators that our higher power is supposed to keep their kind away. I doubt they’d let Gojids exercise patronage to her, once they discover that.

My faint curiosity wondered what sorts of beliefs the Terrans were governed by. Carlos’ words implied that they did have religions, which must shape their society’s morality. Perhaps their gods offered wisdom such as only killing when necessary, and giving their quarry swift deaths? That could explain their prey-like conventions on prisoners and warfare.

Our van paused by a secured gate, where more humans waved it into a large paved area. The vehicle parked itself by a hangar bay, and the operators switched off the ignition. The UN soldiers stalked around to open the rear hatch.

A dark corner of my mind fed me awful ideas about what condition the Gojid refugees were in. What if the predators lost patience with the more fearful individuals while we were in transit? What if being around this many prey animals at once stirred the humans’ appetite, even if they didn’t want it to? This had to be a massive temptation.

“What are you waiting for, Sovlin?” Samantha waved a hand impatiently. “Get a move on it.”

Anton snaked his fingers around my wrist, steadying me as I stumbled out of the van. The predator’s skin was slick and oily; the touch sent a shudder through my veins. I tried to use my surroundings to ground myself, and forget about my proximity to the Terran.

There were no hints of any pens, suspicious contraptions, or butchering tools. This appeared like the helpful facility the predators proclaimed it to be. Thousands of Gojids were milling about, while humans lingered by designated assistance tents. The largest line was at a station labelled for locating loved ones.

“You can’t have gotten many people off planet,” I muttered. “Why give them hope?”

Carlos crossed his arms. “Such a cynic. If we reunite a handful of friends or family, then it’s worth it.”

The female guard shook her head in disapproval as well. She fished a yellow object out of her pocket, and tugged down the outer skin. The soft flesh below had to be from a plant, judging by the lack of eyes, limbs, or blood. Was she offering me food? I wasn’t hungry.

To my bewilderment, Samantha took a bite out of the clasped vegetation. The seeds in the half-eaten object confirmed that it was a fruit, rather than any animal organ. This predator was chowing down on prey snacks, right before my eyes! I thought it might be curiosity what our food tasted like, but she seemed too bored for it to be interest.

Marcel could have eaten fruit? I thought the only way to feed him was to sacrifice a crew member, I mused, with a guilty pang. Stars, are these humans even predators at all?

Samantha’s forward-facing eyes locked on me. “Why are you looking at me like that?!”

“You…you eat plants?” I squeaked.

Anton nodded. “We’re omnivores, Sovlin. Humans can eat meat, but that’s not the main part of our diet.”

“Umnuver?” I struggled to pronounce the tonal word, since no equivalent existed in my language. “Okay. Uh, sorry for gawking. M-maybe just show me something you want my help with?”

Carlos steered me toward a large dormitory, palming his chin in thought. This predator had strange green markings across his arm. Was that some sort of customary brand, for males in their service? Maybe it was a way of denoting his kill count, or ancestral heritage? The olive-skinned human didn’t notice me studying him, which was a relief.

The male guard checked that no Gojids were watching, before pointing to the far end of the bunks. “See that group huddling over there? How they seem to be protecting that chap with the beige claws?”

“What about it?” I answered.

“That guy they’re shielding has been unresponsive to any of our orders,” Samantha chimed in. “Completely ignoring us.”

Carlos nodded. “Which isn’t the issue. Lots of Gojids haven’t been very cooperative, because they’re afraid or otherwise. But this particular fellow, it’s like everyone tries to get him away as quickly as possible.”

“So what? You, um, want me to get this one to listen to you? I can’t guarantee I can do that.”

The predator shook his head. “Just find out why they’re hiding him. If he’s a celebrity, a religious leader, a politician…I don’t know. If he’s important to you all, we can give him special treatment.”

The Gojid in question wasn’t anyone that I recognized. If I didn’t know him, it was unlikely he was famous enough that large percentages of our people would pick him out. A suspicion flickered in my mind, that this one had some sort of disability.

Everyone knew that predators practiced the “survival of the fittest” maxim of nature. The humans had ample emotions, but would they knowingly expend resources on a deficient individual? Someone with a permanent handicap wouldn’t be helpful for rebuilding our species, to the predatory mindset. Surely, they’d want that trait wiped out of the gene pool.

Humans probably would think they’re doing us a favor, with how limited our numbers are. They’d never understand why we nurse an individual who cannot care for themselves, or can never live a normal life.

“Er, I’ll check in,” I growled. “Don’t come with me. Nobody will talk to you.”

Samantha tossed the finished fruit peel into a waste bin. “Fine. Don’t try to run. That band on your ankle will tell us where you are.”

My conscience was torn, as I wandered over to the group. While I owed the predators an immense debt, one I could never atone for, sacrificing another person’s life felt immoral. Perhaps I should have just refused to help; if I didn’t know anything, it couldn’t be used against the poor guy.

A Gojid female watched my approach, and pointed a claw at me. “Stop. What do you want?”

I halted in my tracks. “Is the young man there alright? Have the predators done something to him?”

“Nothing like that,” she muttered. “Why should we trust you? You just came with a bunch of their soldiers. We saw you go through the checkpoint.”

“I’m a high-ranking Gojid officer that was taken prisoner during the war.” The words were automatic, as if some other persona jumped behind the wheel. “The second they released me, I’m doing what I can to help…under the circumstances. You might know me; my name is Captain Sovlin.”

Her eyes widened. “The Sovlin? It’s an honor, sir. Um, I’m Berna, and the silent one’s Talpin.”

“Nice to meet you. May I ask again what the issue is?”

“Tal is deaf. He can’t hear any of the predators’ commands, and they’re starting to get belligerent. We’re trying to guide him, but it’s a matter of time before they figure it out.”

“How long do you think you can keep them in the dark? The humans aren’t stupid.”

“A few days, at most. But every hour we keep my brother alive is worth it to me.”

I studied the deaf Gojid, noticing the confusion plastered across his features. A burning feeling crawled into my throat. The length of Talpin’s lower spines suggested that he had just reached adulthood. This teenager had so much of his life ahead of him, and his family circle would mourn his loss immensely.

The UN soldiers were waiting, expecting a full report. Yes, it was a single life to earn the humans’ favor; one that would be terminated soon anyways. But there were so many fatalities on my conscience. As it were, that count was more than I could live with.

I couldn’t let another person die because of me. Not a single one. The Terrans would resent my disobedience, but any threats paled in comparison to a novel source of guilt.

“I understand. I suggest that you lay low as possible,” I said with a soft tone. “Take care of yourselves.”

Talpin waved at me, blissfully ignorant to the dilemma in my mind. I shuffled back toward the predators, while a choking sickness clamped down on my stomach. Their hideous eyes searched mine for any clues. Carlos barked a question, but the translated meaning was lost beneath my swirling thoughts.

“Sovlin? Talk to me, buddy.” Anton patted my shoulder, and I flinched at the contact. “You look shaken up. What’s the matter?”

Samantha narrowed her eyes. “What did they tell you? If there’s a threat, we can try to de-escalate the situation. That is part of our training, you know.”

“I’m sorry. N-no one is in danger. But I can’t tell you,” I whimpered.

“What do you mean, ‘You can’t tell us?!’” the female predator hissed.

“Your reaction could be drastic. I can’t get someone else killed…no matter how b-bad I feel about Marcel. Just throw me back in my cell, okay? Please.”

She blinked. “Nobody is getting killed. Have humans ever displayed violence toward you? Either you trust us to conduct ourselves with kindness and compassion, or you haven’t reformed at all. Pick one.”

“I…I don’t know. Shit, I don’t know!”

“Sovlin, we are trying to help these people. You have my word that no harm will befall any of them. Not unless there is zero alternative,” Carlos growled.

I squeezed my eyes shut. Feeling empathy was a far cry from the altruistic disregard of genealogy. Humans wouldn’t be a strong, warrior species without making a few logical sacrifices. It might stupefy them, that we burdened ourselves with so-called debility. Would honor be enough to compel the predator guards to spare Talpin?

The lawyer jostled my arm again. “You’re panicking. I can see that. Whatever predator nonsense you all are convinced of, it’s dead wrong. We are nothing like the Arxur.”

“Yes, but…he’s deaf!” I blurted.

The humans recoiled. All of their expressions seemed stunned, from how their eyebrows shot up toward their hairline. I don’t think that possibility even crossed their mind. Why would it, when they would never engage in such an impractical undertaking themselves?

Shit, what have I done? You couldn’t keep your fat mouth shut, and let a teenager live his final days in peace? I berated myself. You’re a weak-minded, selfish asshole, Sovlin. You should’ve spaced yourself back on your ship.

Samantha scratched her head. “Was that so hard? I think I can take care of this.”

The UN guards stalked toward the group, and I tailed behind them in mute horror. My brain was screaming at them to stop, but I couldn’t muster the words. The self-hatred reached a new high; my will to live felt depleted. Were the predators going to take Talpin away from his family? Execute him in front of the watching crowd?

The female human approached, without drawing her weapon, and gestured toward the deaf youth. Talpin screeched, as he saw the armed predators’ attention on him. With bristling spines, he tried to crawl under his bunk. The Gojid cluster gaped at me with looks of absolute betrayal; tears swelled in my eyes.

“How could you, Sovlin?!” Berna jumped between the Terrans and her brother, flexing her claws in defiance. “I thought you were a hero! A man who would die for our planet.”

I collapsed to my knees, hugging my chest. “I’m so sorry. I…I trusted them.”

“P-please, don’t kill him, predators. I’ll give you whatever you want!” the sister protested.

Samantha dropped to one leg. “We’re not going to hurt anyone. Can he understand me now?”

She made a series of animated gestures, concurrent with her speech. Talpin watched her with a blank stare, trembling. Her clawless fingers curled in strange motions, but they didn’t seem random. My misery gave way to confusion, as I tried to understand what she was doing. Was this some non-verbal form of communication?

That’s not hunger or disgust in her eyes, I don’t think.

“Sign language,” Carlos explained, spotting my bafflement. “It’s how deaf people communicate on our planet. Do your translators work on it?”

“N-no. Only audible language; that’s why tail s-signals don’t translate,” I stammered.

The female predator lowered her hands. “Dammit. Please tell him we’re going to find a way to talk to him, Gojids. Ask him for a little patience.”

Berna gaped at the UN soldiers. “Okay? Thank you.”

My mind was spinning. The humans created an entire gesture language for those who lacked hearing? Did that mean that they catered to other ailments too; that individuals like Talpin could live normal lives? This suggested the limits of their nurturing went much farther than I imagined.

The Arxur would have considered any hindered offspring as prey, lumping it in the same category as their food. Then again, they abandoned their children days after birth, whereas Marcel spoke as if humans kept contact with their progeny. With their empathetic behavior toward our younglings, I couldn’t imagine they left their kids to fend for themselves.

“I don’t understand. You speak a language for deaf people, but you can hear?” I murmured.

Samantha raised her shoulders briefly. “My brother is deaf. Was from birth.”

Berna’s eyes widened. “Your parents reared a deficient offspring? Reworked their whole lives for it…kept it?”

“What the fuck? Of course they ‘kept’ him!” she spat.

The Gojid flinched. “S-sorry. Shit, I meant no offense, predator. I thought you’d care about individual contributions.”

“There are more ways to enhance society than by being the pinnacle of physical perfection.” Anton met my gaze, though replying to Berna. It was like he knew my thoughts followed a similar track. “One of our greatest astrophysicists was a quadriplegic for decades; fully dependent on the care of others, unable to talk without a speech synthesizer. Brilliant man.”

I twisted my claws, pondering their words. Though I regretted my behavior toward Marcel, my understanding of humans was limited to the scope of my prior knowledge. Zarn had spoken in ghastly detail about their cruelty and malice. Our briefing videos encapsulated those heinous acts, and confirmed the unthinkable level of viciousness abiding within them.

Even in Terran domain, all I see is compassion. Where is the humanity that the Federation saw? Wouldn’t such a brutish nature shine through, somewhere?

Seeing their redeeming qualities, such as how they were capable of empathy, was a start. However, these primates were nothing at all like any scientist predicted. Predators’ entire purpose in an ecosystem was to weed out the weak. They were natural selection itself!

“You’re quite right, humans. You are nothing like the Arxur,” I admitted.

“We’re not. We want you to help us beat them, Sovlin, but the UN needed to see that you trust us first.” A hard glint flashed in Carlos’ brown eyes. “I’m satisfied that your remorse is genuine. What do you say we spend a few hours here, then we talk shop?”

“That translated as, um, discussing work?”

“Touché. We’re drumming up plans to take the fight to the Arxur, and to bring whatever is left of your cradle back into our hands. Would you be willing to look them over? Perhaps serve alongside us?”

I realized that, in spite of my visceral reaction to their features, I almost liked these humans. They had a certain charisma, when they articulated their lofty intentions. Our cradle would be little more than rubble now, but its symbolism counted for something.

A few thousand Gojids might’ve survived in bunkers, and these strange predators were their last hope. The UN was giving me a chance to offset a fraction of the damage I'd caused. That wasn't the sort of offer I could pass up.

“There’s nothing I’d like more. Count me in.”

⋯ ✧ ⋯ ✧ ⋯

Chapter 35
Memory transcription subject:

Captain Sovlin,
Federation Fleet Command

Date [standardized human time]:
October 6, 2136

The bulletproof vest afforded to me by the predators was snug around my spines, but nearly fell off my shoulders. Its shape was not designed for the rotund Gojid species. The slender curvature of the human spine was a polar opposite, evolved for grace and flexibility.

I knew the armor might save my life, but I wish I waited longer to don it. My bristles were being compressed at irritating angles, and the nearest soldiers seemed annoyed by my inability to sit still. The humans were sandwiched together in the shuttle, brushing shoulders with each other. I was glad to be at the end, so I could lean toward the wall.

Samantha traded places with Carlos halfway through the ride. She bore an obvious disdain for me, but the male guard had enough of my fidgeting. Many of the general soldiers curled their lips in contempt as well; I wasn’t winning any popularity contests with these predators. I was grateful we were only a minute out from the cattle vessel.

“Did we succeed at paralyzing the Arxur transport?” I asked the female chaperone.

Her eyelashes fluttered in annoyance. “Yes. Were you not listening to the damn announcements?”

“Relax, Sam. It was an innocent question,” Carlos sighed. “I’m sure he just zoned out.”

“You feel sorry for the racist war criminal?” a soldier called out.

I saw a few humans nod their heads in agreement, which caused me to lower my gaze. There wouldn’t be many tears shed by anyone other than the UN brass, if the Arxur gunned me down today. Not that I blamed them; an honorable death wasn’t the worst thing I could think of. Dying scared me more than death.

I wish I had a weapon, so I could actually help. I don’t want to stay back, and let them do all the fighting.

“Well, that’s great news,” I said, ignoring the jab. “Can I have a gun?”

“No,” a chorus of voices answered in unison.

I waved my claws dismissively. “Worth a shot.”

The shuttle lurched beneath my paws, and my vest pressed harder against my spines. There was going to be some light bruising tomorrow, if I lived past this battle. Our craft latched onto an Arxur wing, attaching itself to the immobilized transport. We inched forward so that our airlock stood across from theirs.

A vac-suited predator slipped into our emergency airlock, and I strained to see his movements through the window. The Terran unfurled a walkway on our side, then floated across to the Arxur vessel with a gentle push. All that tied him to us was a thin rope on his waist. He tested a red lever with a feeble hand, and confirmed that it wasn’t locked.

The human nodded to himself, and used some sort of suction technology to adhere the tunnel to the enemy ship. His feet clicked onto the ground, as the artificial gravity initiated. Once the corridor was sealed from the vacuum, he raised his thumb to the rest of us. I didn’t understand the signal, but the others took it as a go-ahead.

The UN soldiers trundled out of the ship, wielding massive rifles. While the predators possessed few natural gifts, they were saddled with a truckload of gear. Their warriors were clad head-to-toe in black armor, including a hard shell atop their heads. Once they shoved reflective goggles over their eyes, humans looked like homogenous, impassive machines.

“Stick behind us, Sovlin.” Samantha rose to her feet, falling into the rear of the pack. “We can’t leave you here to get captured. Take cover, and stay out of the way ‘til you’re needed.”

Silence fell over our entourage, as the primates crossed the cattle ship’s threshold. I couldn’t help but notice the humans’ slinking posture, as though they were stalking prey in a shaded forest. They were crouched to a fraction of their normal height, with steps that were furtive and calculated. Their guns swiveled in every direction, searching for a target to pounce on.

With a hint of reluctance, my paws followed them down the tunnel. There were some short bursts of gunfire, as they pumped a few unprepared Arxur full of lead. I suppressed a chuckle, knowing it would make me seem deranged. The enemy would raise the alarm now, but I relished that we got the drop on them.

My attention switched to the reptilian interior, taking mental notes of its facilities. The Federation would kill for intelligence like this. The atmosphere was musty, but the lighting was rich and plentiful. The hygiene of the enemy ship surprised me as well; it didn’t reek of rotten flesh or blood. I guess those savages understood basic disease transmission after all.

We followed the entryway a few hundred paces, before we reached a bend in the path. The team leader poked his head around the corner, and immediately recoiled. A barrage of bullets decimated the wall, where his shell-cap poked out moments earlier. He ducked back behind cover, hugging his weapon to his chest.

“8 or 9 hostiles arming themselves, and taking positions,” he hissed. “They’re waiting for us.”

We have more numbers than that, but the Arxur have a clear line of sight. They’re going to nail us as soon as we advance.

A human rolled a metal canister across the floor, which released a milky plume of smoke. Irritants dispersed through the hallway, and I squinted to see anything. There was no way the Arxur could determine our position, if I could barely see my claws in front of me. Shrouded in the haze of silver mist, the Terrans stepped out from behind their refuge.

The Arxur sprayed bullets in our direction, hoping to connect with something. These sounds helped the humans key in on their positions, and they spewed their own rounds back in return. Terrans seemed to fare better in low visibility, with their remarkable adaptiveness. The silhouetted movement I glimpsed in the mist suggested a few grays were hit.

As the smoke dissipated, the primates sprang toward any makeshift shelter they could find. Carlos pulled me behind a supply cart, and popped his gun over the top. Samantha sprawled on the floor beside him. Her hands were steady as she gazed down the scope, and fired at an Arxur attempting to fall back. I didn’t know the grays could retreat.

“I imagine, down that main staircase, we’ll find living quarters, the cattle pens, and the bridge,” Samantha growled. “They don’t want us to get to anything vital.”

The female human stood to get a better look, and inched forward to join another UN cluster. My eyes drifted to the Arxur she shot, who was bleeding profusely. The enemy bastard was still twitching, until another Terran soldier unloaded a clip into its head. That was overkill, but hey, I wasn’t judging.

Samantha caressed her rifle with a gloved hand, and waved for Carlos and I to follow. Hesitant as I was to move, the handful of hostile survivors were regrouping with their brethren. The Terrans blinding every combatant caught the Arxur off-guard. It forced them to make concessions, and await backup.

The grays haven’t fought a true enemy in a long time, have they? I mused. They haven’t been on the back foot for a second in this war. Our weakness has made them complacent.

There was no sound from the presumed Arxur position, and I guessed they were lying in wait. The UN contingent advanced with caution, creeping toward the stairway. Their boots glided across the metal, as light as the patter of rain. Whether they were coached by instinct, training, or generational experience, I did not know.

A grating voice rumbled over the PA. “Greetings, fellow hunters. I take it you don’t appreciate that we, ah, stole your catch.”

Several human predators startled, and their attention shifted overhead. My jaw almost dropped to the floor; the Arxur never conversed so eloquently with us. We translated their dialects at first contact, but I couldn’t remember them enunciating anything but vulgar threats in my lifetime. It was incredible that they had words for “greetings” or “appreciate.”

“We would’ve offered to split the haul, if we realized our intrusion sooner,” the Arxur continued. “You made things much easier for us, and we’re not entirely ungrateful. You already learned that Gojids make excellent slaves, judging by your companion.”

I bared my teeth, incensed that this monstrosity thought I was a human plaything. While I was a Terran prisoner, that was a far cry from servitude and degradation. There was nothing I had been forced to do; my presence on this mission was voluntary, and my treatment was fairer than I deserved.

Carlos nudged me, pointing to a blinking red light on the ceiling. There was a camera tracking our movements, and granting the enemy a full view of our advance. He raised only his middle finger, and several of his counterparts copied the gesture. I didn’t understand what that meant either, but I guessed it was something hateful.

“Go fuck yourselves!” the male guard shouted.

Probably that. Note to self.

“Ah, to be a young race again. Let’s get that aggression out of our systems. Then, after, we should pool our resources to bring the lesser species to heel.” The reptile sounded almost disappointed, as though it would enjoy a test of strength. “Anything else would be…wasteful, when our interests are aligned. As loathsome as ‘sharing’ is, there’s enough food to go around.”

Did those demons just offer to ally with humanity against the Federation?! My blood boiled at the thought. It had to be a trap, since everyone knew the Arxur were incapable of inter-species cooperation. They couldn’t get along with themselves. The grays were locked in a global bloodbath, which jeopardized their world’s survival, when we found them.

The prospect of the Terrans switching sides was unnerving, all the same. The clawless “omnivores” hadn’t been welcomed into the galaxy with open arms. The lack of clarity from our factions meant threats could still reside within the Federation. Would humans view siding with monsters as the only way to save their Earth?

Carlos gunned down the camera lens with prejudice, and answered the question for me. His knuckles were strained against the cloth coverings, from being clenched around his rifle. The soldier at the advance’s forefront raised a fist, and our posse shuffled to a halt astride of the staircase. Odds were, the enemy was gathering in the deck underneath us.

“Fire in the hole!” a human voice declared.

A UN soldier lobbed a grenade into the open area, and we watched it clatter down the incline. The resulting explosion detonated atop any Arxur in the vicinity. I heard a gurgling scream, as if shrapnel hit one of the reptiles in the throat. My predatory allies moved down the first steps, and followed it up with another explosive toss. That should be enough to get the enemy to move back.

The primates bounded down the last of the staircase, and jammed down their firing triggers. I followed Samantha’s movements, and tried to keep my head low. We took refuge behind a trash can, in what appeared to be a mess hall. There were blood-speckled trays and reading materials left abandoned on the tables.

What do you know? Eating sentients is a communal activity, I guess.

Arxur gunfire peppered the walls around us, and took down several humans. Other Terrans stepped in as soon as they saw a counterpart felled, dragging them to safety. Attempts to stymie the bleeding looked hopeless, in many cases, but their efforts were charged with emotion. It was mind-boggling how a predator’s warrior class could forge such deep bonds.

How they could even think of their fellow man, during the insanity of battle, was beyond me. The amount of Arxur tickled every flighty urge in my DNA, and overstimulation made my head swim. This wasn’t at all like my revenge fantasies. I was helpless, without any weapon, if one of them lunged at me.

I could sense several reptilian eyes on me. From their vantage point, dinner just walked in front of a firing squad. Malicious snarls sent in my direction told me what they saw in my form. The humans, for all their unwanted teeth baring, had never seemed so “distracted” by me.

“S-stay calm, Sovlin. You hate predators. You want them to burn, rot, and die in agony,” I murmured.

Samantha snorted. “Gee, thanks.”

“Not you. You’re different.”

“Whatever you—"

A stray bullet grazed the female’s headgear. She sensed it clip her cap, and fell back as a kneejerk reaction. The soldier dragged herself back up against the waste bin, with erratic breathing. After taking a moment to collect her wits, she worked to get her rifle situated.

Guilt flashed through my mind, realizing my distraction almost killed her. Calling my guards friends would be a stretch, since that required a mutual respect. But they had become familiar faces, and I didn’t wish for anything to happen to them. There had to be some way for me to help, rather than impede their progress.

Carlos was crouched a few paces deeper, using an upturned table as a shelter. Several UN soldiers were positioned there, coordinating fire. My eyes widened in alarm as I saw an Arxur duo attempting to encircle them. I shouted to warn the humans, but the deafening pops of gunfire drowned out my words.

Panic fluttered in my chest, as a reptile straightened its rifle. Sitting here and doing nothing wasn’t an option; Samantha was too rattled from her encounter to react in time. The mangled Arxur corpse, downed by a grenade at the base of the staircase, caught my eye. A crazy thought leapt into my head, as I glimpsed the bloodied gun in its grip.

“SOVLIN! What the fuck are you—" the female human began.

I dashed out behind cover, and retraced my short steps into the room. The tile was slick with blood, which made traction a struggle. Prying the firearm from the beast’s lifeless grasp, I tried to line up the shot. My heart was hammering at a million parsecs an hour, and my paws quivered too much to steady it.

The lead Arxur fired off the first shot, nailing one of Carlos’ companions in the back of the neck. The other humans whirled around, but they couldn’t react in the half-second it would take to execute them all. Gritting my teeth, I tried to lock my wrists. I released several rounds, praying I wouldn’t accidentally hit the Terrans.

Two of my five bullets nailed the first Arxur, and it crumpled to the floor. Its partner stumbled over the body, which gave the primates enough time to swivel around. An unfamiliar Terran blew its head off with panicked motions. Carlos turned his masked skull, looking for the source of the shots that saved him. His gaze faced me, as I skittered back to Samantha.

The female snatched the firearm from my grip, tucking it under her arm.

“You’re really going to take the gun away?” I groaned. “I saved…”

She offered a grudging sigh. “You saved Carlos’ life.”

“I’m good at killing…for a Gojid. Let me help, please.”

“Not a chance. Don’t even think about pulling a stunt like that again.”

I chewed at my claws, and leaned back against the wall. Several human corpses were strewn about the entry point, suggesting many hadn’t been as lucky as Carlos. These Terran soldiers were resilient, but it was evident Arxur marksmen had wicked accuracy.

About half of our active allies appeared to be nursing injuries, which spoke to an unrivaled ability to persist through pain. Then again, I couldn’t tell when crimson bloodstains were theirs, or a comrade’s. Regardless, our ranks weren't unscathed.

From what I could make out of the scenery, the grays had suffered their fair share of casualties too. Their numbers were whittled down to ten or so, by my estimation. The UN warriors were starting to gain ground, and flush the enemy out. I don’t think the reptilians were prepared to fend off a larger contingent of predators.

The hostile gunfire ceased without warning, and I tilted my head in bewilderment. A firearm skidded across the floor, followed by a series of others. A handful of Arxur rose to their full height, watching the primates’ next move.

The humans paused their barrage, suspicion glowing in their eyes. What in the name of the Protector was this?

⋯ ✧ ⋯ ✧ ⋯

Chapter 44
Memory transcription subject:

Captain Kalsim,
Krakotl Alliance Command

Date [standardized human time]:
October 9, 2136

As soon as we departed Krakotl space, it became evident that the humans had been tracking our movements. The predators were lurking in the shadows along our starry route; two ambushes were sprung on the fleet during the first day of travel. The primates knew that we were coming, and that was enough to unsettle the crew.

But the humans were afraid, from what I could tell. Their attacks seem devoted to stalling, and chipping away at our resources. Larger Terran ships had FTL-disruptors on their hulls, which could be deployed as soon as we came within range. They would dart in for a missile run while we were dazed, then vanish just as quickly.

Why do they flee after a single strike? These techniques seem too cowardly to be borne of predators.

Nonetheless, I adjusted personnel rotations, so that our vessel was combat-ready at all times. I allowed myself only a short nap after the second ambush, just to refresh my wits. There was no time for a full night’s rest until the enemy resurfaced.

Thyon was working overtime as well, compiling data to predict the Terrans’ next appearance. Our vessel was going to nail the humans, next time they tried anything. If their attempts at disrupting our operations were this lousy, they must lack confidence in their combat abilities.

“This locale seems like the likeliest spot for an ambush. The EM radiation from the system’s pulsar makes our sensors and targeting wonky,” the first officer said. “Though, perhaps I’m mistaken. It would affect their targeting too.”

My feathers ruffled with disquiet. “I suspect humans’ reliance on targeting is less than ours. They have a backup system in their brains.”

“Should we advise the fleet to reroute? If I’m correct on Terran whereabouts, there’s less than a minute before they activate the disruptors.”

“Let’s not do anything hasty, Thyon. Their ships can outpace us, so we’ll just be pushing this off to a later date. We face these predator pests here, on our terms.”

The Farsul officer swallowed nervously, and studied his readout. I couldn’t blame the big-eared guy for feeling discomfort about engaging the humans blind. Our instinctual fear wasn’t conducive to off-the-cuff maneuvers, and precise calculations under stress. Krakotl could muster aggression, sure, but that desperation wasn’t controlled.

But Jala wasn’t bogged down by chemicals. If I placed her behind the weapons station, she could recalibrate our artillery on a dime. We didn’t have to worry about fear addling her senses. There was a reason I twisted the brass’ wing, not to lock her up in an asylum like they wanted to. It was in our best interest to use people like her against the predators.

I cleared my throat. “Jala, assume control of weapons. Switch to manual override, and hit the first ship you see with whatever you like.”

The female Krakotl shoved a younger officer out of her way, and pecked the buttons with giddiness. She didn’t need to be told twice. It was rare to see anyone else so thrilled to carry out orders, especially when those involved being flung into combat. My second-in-command wouldn't miss the clues, if they were shoved in his face.

“Captain, answer me honestly,” Thyon whispered. “Does Jala have Predator Disease?”

I lowered my voice. “That terminology is ignorant; predators do feel fear. Jala is an asset that I have under control. She knows I’m the only thing stopping her from being thrown in a deep, dark hole.”

“I don’t believe for a second that predators feel anything…but she has more in common with them, either way. How can you trust her not to side with them?”

“Even people with her condition don’t side with people who want to eat them. I’ve heard that has a way of shortening your lifespan.”

“You don’t say.”

The Farsul transferred the projected enemy coordinates onto the sensor grid. By his estimates, the humans were camped within a gas giant’s ring. It seemed a suitable position to lie in wait. The planet’s gravitational field added further disturbance to sensor readings, and the icy ring particles were indistinguishable from a quiet vessel.

That’s actually some solid analytics from Thyon. I suppose I’m fortunate the guy the Federation saddled me with is halfway intelligent.

The first officer also noted the maximum range of an FTL disruptor. It stood to reason that the humans would wait until the bulk of the fleet was within the pulse’s umbrella. I highlighted the blast zone circumference on my screen, using their approximate location. Now, it was a matter of forging ahead and waiting.

“Navigations, as soon as we hit the edge of that red circle, disengage warp,” I squawked. “If we time this right, the humans will think we’re stunned. Just as they show themselves, we’ll be ready to fire.”

Thyon blinked in surprise. “Bold plan. If we’re off by a few seconds, we’ll get dazed alongside everyone else.”

“And if we drop in too early, the humans will know we’re onto them. Of course, we don’t know they’re here for sure. We could be chasing ghosts…but I’m trusting your work.”

“Thank you, sir. Shouldn’t we tip off the fleet though?”

“Negative. The predators may have breached our comms.”

Other friendly vessels may have come to similar conclusions, but our role as the Krakotl flagship was to seize the initiative. Defeating a predator necessitated brashness. I don’t think even the meticulous humans accounted for us turning the tables. They were under the impression that everyone in the Federation was weak, and that might serve us well.

The fear plastered across the bridge crew’s faces was apparent; the inexperienced enlistees weren’t keen on hurling a multi-billion credit ship into a predator’s trap. To be fair, this was the kind of action that earned reprimands from Alliance Command if it backfired. We had one chance to validate our decisions.

My file does say I take ‘unnecessary risks’, and attributes my success to luck. I imagine Thyon read that dossier before boarding.

For better or for worse, I always asked myself what a predator would do. Trying to predict their moves or understand their thinking was easy, once it was a habit. This raid was one final job, before passing the baton to someone younger. What better way to cap off my career than by vanquishing the greatest threat of our time?

I fluttered over to the navigations station, ready to intervene if the technician froze. Our dot was almost overlapping the perilous area. Thyon was itching to issue the disengage order, but I didn’t want to jump the gun. We couldn’t allow the riskiness to inhibit our patience.

My breathing hitched as we entered the pulse threshold. “A little further…real space, now!”

A head-on view of a gas giant materialized on the viewport. The dull orange mass, surrounded by a glistening ring, was a sight to behold. My talons stiffened, as the feeling of being watched sank in. I couldn’t see any enemy ships, but I could sense their unholy presence.

“No sign of human activity—" Thyon began.

Thousands of friendly vessels appeared around us without warning. The Federation fleet was evidently reeling from the effects of the disruptor signal. Lithe Terran ships swarmed out of the ring, and descended on the nearest Krakotl vessels with fury.

Jala’s wings extended to their full span, as she began firing missiles at will. Several projectiles slammed into an enemy bomber, and it was terminated mid-swoop. More explosives followed close behind, synced with whirring kinetics that pelted their shields.

The humans were pushed back by my crazed Krakotl, long enough for some friendlies to catch their bearings. Our allies’ aim was clearly rattled without sensors, and most plasma beams missed their mark by a long shot. Nonetheless, the predators determined the mission was a wash. They weren’t going to take the chance of a stray hit connecting.

There’s only a few dozen ships in this ambush, anyways. The Terran military didn’t lend sufficient support.

“They’re retreating. Don’t let them get away!” the Farsul first officer exclaimed.

“All Federation ships, fire at will.” I barked over the comms channel. “I don’t care if you miss! Hurl everything you’ve got ready at their position.”

Jala was happy to oblige those orders, and dispensed another round of missiles toward the gas giant’s cover. That was where the Terrans were trying to vanish for emergency warp. None of our explosives connected with an opponent, but they did pack a punch to the ring itself. Ice fragments were flung out from the epicenter, and some shrapnel found its way into human armor.

The navigations officer maneuvered us to the edge of the ring; the proximity was close enough to get a visual. A few predator craft were rendered inoperable, or ripped apart by debris. Cheers erupted across the bridge, as they saw the devastation we unleashed. I tried to mimic pleasure, but gunning humans down just made me feel numb.

My eyes lingered on the wreckage in the viewport. “Nice work, Jala. We must’ve taken out a number in the double digits…in no small part, due to your fortitude.”

“Don’t mention it. That was fun!” she trilled. “Just a shame our skirmish was so short. I was expecting more of a scrap.”

Thyon narrowed his eyes. “It’s not a shame that our victory was decisive. It makes it more likely that our flight to Earth will continue unimpeded.”

I tuned out their bickering. My focus was on scanning a motionless Terran vessel via manual input. Ship sensors had been fully automated since before I was born. At close-range though, it should be possible to work through the interference with operator assistance.

The human craft I scrutinized had its hull caved in, which suggested debris impact at high velocity. It was mostly intact, but life support and propulsions were knocked offline. Some part of me itched to know if its pilot was still alive. Future generations would ask about these Earthlings, and nobody could provide an adequate explanation. This was a pristine opportunity to document a sapient predator’s mannerisms.

“Silence on the bridge! Comms, make sure all transmissions are being recorded,” I screeched. “I want everyone here to know the enemy, so I’m hailing that venting wreck. Consider it a crash course on predators.”

Thyon gasped. “What? What makes you think that demon will answer?”

I tilted my head. There was no guarantee a human would accept our communication attempt, but it was worth a try. While seeing its face would make the crew shudder, there was no feasible risk. Its weapons and escape options were severed, and it was smart enough to know that.

The outbound hail was sent with a swipe of my talons, against the protests of the crew. A tense silence filled the air, as our signal was extended to the crippled foe. There was no response for several seconds, which only added to the crew’s nerves. Did these people think a predator could teleport on deck through a call?

I could almost sense the Terran’s bewilderment; it was weighing whether to hear our message. Curiosity must have won out, because a pair of frosty blue eyes appeared on screen. The ferocity of its gaze sent several crewmates ducking for cover; their color looked cold and unnatural. The beast had a laceration across its forehead, and was dabbing it with a towel to keep the blood out of its vision.

It’s wounded. Maybe it’s not thinking straight, so we can pry some intel from it.

I couldn’t say that looking at it didn’t give me the creeps, even after decades of dealing with predators. This creature was more intelligent than anything I eliminated in the wild. There were only a few clumps of hair across its face, which made it look alien and bare.

“What do you want? I don’t need your mockery, birds,” it gurgled.

I resisted the urge to avert my gaze, and instead tried to make neutral observations. Beneath that petrifying visage, there were signs that the creature was rattled. The slightest furrow of its brow suggested fear, and the way its jaw tightened indicated pain. It realized its death was imminent; that knowledge overshadowed its last moments.

I raised a wing in a noncommittal gesture. “Nobody is mocking you. I just want to talk.”

“You’ve got to be shitting me.” It leaned closer to the camera, close enough to make out the veins in its eyes. “What makes you think I want to talk to you?! Enlighten me.”

“A hunch. I figured a pack predator wouldn’t want to die alone. If I’m wrong on that, you can end this transmission now.”

Thyon was staring at me like I’d grown a third wing, while Jala was observing the exchange with amusement. I had my reasons for fielding this call in the public eye. The crew needed to see affirmation of my theories, after the skeptical reception I observed. It would be a critical lapse in understanding, to presume they shared the Arxur’s solitary behavioral patterns.

The human bared its teeth, and shook its head in disbelief. It placed its chin on its hands, then refocused those horrific eyes on the camera. Frost spiraled from its plump lips, which suggested the cabin temperature was frigid. With only a stringy flaxen mane, I didn’t imagine it would last without environmental regulation for long.

“You never answered my question,” the beast sighed. “What is it you want?”

“I want to rescue you from that icebox. Surrender yourself to our custody, peacefully, and I’ll see that you survive. You can ensure that your culture is remembered.”

“Thanks, but no thanks. How fucking stupid do you think I am? Death is better than what you lot do to human prisoners.”

“You have my word that I’ll hold you in fair conditions. You don’t want to die. I can see your fear.”

The predator blinked slowly, and hugged its arms together to conserve warmth. It wasn’t ready to give up key information now, but if I managed its needs, it might start spilling intelligence. Self-preservation was a driving force in every sapient being.

The human detached a small cutout from its dashboard, and turned it toward the camera. The image was of three snarling, young predators, with the pilot crouched beside them. Another adult primate had an arm around the offspring, and was flashing pearly white fangs. They looked vicious, but…happy.

“That’s my family. I am afraid, but not of my death,” it growled. “I’m afraid that you’re going to kill everyone I love. The only thing that will please you is my whole species purged from existence…and I don’t know if even that will quench your hatred. Please, stop this.”

The transmission cut out abruptly, and I pushed down the lump of pity in my throat. There was the confirmation that humans cared for each other. I hoped that inspired a bit more sympathy from my comrades; the Krakotl government shouldn’t hide humanity’s redeeming attributes. It was enough to establish them as a major, valid threat.

The truth matters, I thought to myself. We’re not going to strip that away on my ship, to make ourselves feel better.

“The predator only has a few hours before its atmosphere is used up. Orders, sir?” Jala asked in an emotionless voice.

I lowered my gaze. “Terminate it. A quick death, Jala. The human refused my offer, and we can’t leave it to be rescued by its brethren.”

The female Krakotl rolled her eyes, but deployed a missile into the drive column. I watched as the wreckage went up in flame. It was merciful to grant the beast a swift end, rather than condemning it to suffocate in that freezing tomb. Still, its death didn’t bring out any positive emotions. Some of the crew seemed moved by its elimination as well, which meant my strategy was a success.

Thyon’s nostrils flared with exasperation. “What were you thinking, Captain?! What would you have done if it accepted your offer?”

“I would’ve stuck it in the brig, like I said,” I answered. “And no, Zarn wouldn’t have gotten within a hundred paces of it. We could contain a single, wounded predator…and it was useful.”

“Useful? What did you gain from that little chat?!”

“Watch your tone, XO; this is my ship. Now, you all know the enemy as I do. You can come to terms with the real reasons for this mission.”

The Farsul first officer gritted his teeth. Thyon was disturbed by my generous view of predators, but he knew protesting on the bridge was out of line. Perhaps he needed to believe falsehoods to maintain his conviction.

All doubts needed to be sorted out before we reached Earth. Assuming the Terran ambushes were resolved, the fleet’s next engagement would pummel everything humanity had into oblivion. When we reached our destination, I hoped my crew would be ready to do what was necessary.

⋯ ✧ ⋯ ✧ ⋯

Capítulo 47

El experto

1970

El fiscal Eric Chastain estaba interrogando al sheriff sobre los dos chavales que el 30 de octubre descubrieron el cuerpo de Chase Andrews en la base de la torre de vigilancia, el examen del forense y la investigación preliminar.

—Sheriff, por favor, díganos qué le hizo creer que Chase Andrews no se cayó de la torre por accidente —continuó Eric—. ¿Qué le hizo pensar que se había cometido un crimen?

—Bueno, una de las primeras cosas en las que me fijé fue en que cerca del cuerpo de Chase no había huellas de pisadas, ni siquiera las suyas. Solo las de los chavales que lo encontraron. Por eso pensé que alguien las habría borrado para ocultar un crimen.

—¿No es también cierto, sheriff, que en el escenario tampoco había huellas dactilares ni huellas de vehículos?

—Sí, es correcto. Los informes del laboratorio decían que en la torre no había huellas dactilares recientes. Ni siquiera en la reja, que alguien debió levantar. Mi ayudante y yo buscamos huellas de vehículos y tampoco las había. Todo ello indicaba que alguien había borrado las pruebas de forma intencionada.

—Por tanto, cuando el informe de laboratorio demostró que esa noche se habían encontrado fibras de lana roja del gorro de la señorita Clark en la ropa de Chase, usted…

—Protesto, su señoría —dijo Tom—. Conduce al testigo. Además, ya se ha establecido que las fibras rojas pudieron transferirse de la ropa de la señorita Clark a la del señor Andrews antes de la noche del 29 al 30 de octubre.

—Aceptada —bramó el juez.

—No tengo más preguntas. Su testigo.

Eric sabía que el testimonio del sheriff no sería de gran utilidad para la acusación, pues ¿qué podía hacer sin huellas dactilares, de pisadas o de vehículos? Pero, aun así, su testimonio tenía suficiente sustancia para convencer al jurado de que alguien había asesinado a Chase y, teniendo en cuenta las fibras rojas, ese alguien bien podría haber sido la señorita Clark.

Tom Milton se acercó al banquillo de los testigos.

—Sheriff, ¿pidió usted u otra persona que viniera un experto para que buscase huellas o pruebas de que se habían borrado dichas pisadas?

—No era necesario. Yo soy experto en eso. El examen de huellas de pisadas es parte del entrenamiento oficial. No necesitaba a otro experto.

—Ya veo. ¿Y había pruebas de que esas pisadas se hubieran borrado? Me refiero, por ejemplo, a si había marcas de que se hubiera usado algún cepillo o rama para borrar las huellas. ¿Se había movido el barro para tapar un barro anterior? ¿Hay alguna prueba, alguna fotografía, de que se hubiera hecho tal cosa?

—No. Yo testifico como experto que bajo la torre no había más pisadas que las nuestras y las de los chavales. Así que alguien tuvo que borrarlas.

—Muy bien. Pero, sheriff, una característica física de la marisma es que las mareas vienen y van, y que el nivel del manto freático varía mucho incluso estando lejos del mar, lo que hace que algunas zonas se sequen por un tiempo y horas después acaben cubiertas de agua. En muchos lugares, cuando el nivel del agua crece, empapa la zona y borra cualquier marca que pueda haber en el barro, como las huellas de pisadas. Y lo deja limpio. ¿Es eso cierto?

—Bueno, sí, puede ser. Pero no hay pruebas de que pasara algo así.

—Tengo aquí la carta de mareas de la noche del 29 al 30 de octubre y, mire, sheriff Jackson, indica que la marea baja tuvo lugar alrededor de medianoche. Por tanto, a la hora en que Chase llegó a la torre y subió los escalones, debió de dejar huellas en el barro húmedo. Pero luego, al llegar la marea y subir la capa freática, sus huellas se borraron. Esa es la razón por la que usted y los chicos dejaron huellas, y la misma razón por la que desaparecieron las de Chase. ¿Le parece eso posible?

Kya asintió ligeramente; era su primera reacción ante un testimonio desde que había empezado el juicio. Había visto muchas veces cómo las aguas de la marisma se tragaban lo sucedido el día anterior: huellas de cuervo junto a un arroyo o pisadas de gato montés junto a un cervatillo muerto desaparecían.

—Bueno, nunca la he visto borrar nada de forma tan completa, así que no lo sé —respondió el sheriff.

—Pero, sheriff, ha dicho que es usted un experto, entrenado en el arte de examinar huellas. ¿Y ahora nos dice que no sabe si esa noche tuvo lugar ese suceso tan corriente?

»Pues no debe de ser tan difícil demostrarlo en un sentido u otro, ¿verdad? Bastaría con ir allí con la marea baja, dejar huellas y comprobar si la marea las borra al llegar.

»Sí, no sería muy difícil determinarlo en un sentido u otro. Por tanto, ¿por qué no se hizo? Ya estamos en un juicio y usted no ofrece prueba alguna de que alguien borrase esas huellas para ocultar un crimen. Lo más probable es que Chase Andrews dejase huellas bajo la torre, pero se borraron con la marea. Y también habría borrado las huellas de quien hubiera subido con él a la torre por diversión. Y, dadas esas circunstancias más que probables, no hay indicio alguno de un crimen. ¿No es así, sheriff?

Ed miró a izquierda, derecha, izquierda, derecha, como si buscara la respuesta en las paredes. La gente se removió en los bancos.

—¿Sheriff? —repitió Tom.

—En mi opinión profesional, resulta improbable que el ciclo normal de las mareas borrase por completo las huellas hasta ese punto. Pero, si bien nada indica que se borrasen esas huellas y la ausencia de pisadas no prueba por sí sola que se cometiera un crimen, hay que…

—Gracias. —Tom se volvió hacia el jurado y repitió las palabras del sheriff—. La ausencia de pisadas no prueba que se cometiera un crimen. Bueno, sigamos. Sheriff, ¿qué pasa con la reja levantada de la torre de vigilancia? ¿La examinaron para buscar huellas dactilares de la señorita Clark?

—Sí, claro que las buscamos.

—¿Y encontraron huellas de la señorita Clark en la reja o en algún otro lugar de la torre?

—No. No, pero tampoco encontramos otras huellas, así que…

El juez se inclinó hacia delante.

—Limítese a responder las preguntas, Ed.

—¿Y cabellos? La señorita Clark tiene el pelo negro y largo. De haber subido a la cima y haberse movido por la plataforma para levantar rejas y esas cosas, debería de haber quedado algún cabello suyo. ¿Encontró alguno?

—No.

La frente del sheriff brillaba.

—El forense testificó que, tras examinar el cuerpo de Chase, no encontró prueba alguna que situara esa noche a la señorita Clark cerca de él. Ah, están esas fibras, claro, pero podrían tener cuatro años. Y ahora nos dice que tampoco había evidencia alguna de que la señorita Clark hubiera estado esa noche en la torre de vigilancia. ¿Es esta afirmación correcta?

—Sí.

—Por tanto, no hay evidencias que apunten a que la señorita Clark estuviera en la torre de vigilancia la noche en que Chase Andrews se precipitó a su muerte. ¿Correcto?

—Es lo que he dicho.

—Eso es un sí.

—Sí, es un sí.

—Sheriff, ¿no es cierto que los chicos que juegan en lo alto de la torre suelen dejarse las rejas levantadas?

—Sí, a veces las dejan levantadas. Pero, como he dicho, suele pasar con la que hay que levantar para salir a la plataforma, no con las demás.

—¿Y no es cierto que la reja de la escalera, y a veces alguna de las otras, se ha dejado levantada tan a menudo que la consideran tan peligrosa como para que su oficina hiciera una petición por escrito al Servicio Forestal con el fin de que lo remediase? —Tom le mostró un documento al sheriff—. ¿Es esta la petición oficial que hizo al Servicio Forestal el 18 de julio del año pasado?

El sheriff miró la hoja.

—Sí. Lo es.

—¿Quién redactó esta petición?

—Yo mismo.

—Por tanto, solo tres meses antes de que Chase Andrews se precipitara a su muerte por una reja levantada en la torre de vigilancia, usted hizo una petición por escrito al Servicio Forestal para pedir que cerraran la torre o aseguraran las rejas para que nadie saliera herido. ¿Es eso correcto?

—Sí.

—Sheriff, ¿quiere hacer el favor de leer al tribunal la última frase del documento que usted remitió al Servicio Forestal? Solo la última frase. Esta.

Entregó el documento al sheriff y señaló la última línea.

El sheriff leyó en voz alta al tribunal:

—«Debo repetir que estas rejas son muy peligrosas y que, de no tomarse medidas, podrían dar pie a alguna lesión grave cuando no a la muerte».

—No tengo más preguntas.

Capítulo 48

Un viaje

1969

El 28 de octubre de 1969, Kya se acercó al muelle de Jumpin’ para despedirse de él, como le había prometido, y luego se dirigió al puerto del pueblo, donde pescadores y camaroneros interrumpieron como siempre su trabajo para mirarla pasar. Los ignoró, amarró la barca y se alejó por la calle principal cargando una gastada maleta de cartón sacada del viejo armario de mamá. No tenía bolso, pero llevaba la mochila llena de libros, además de algo de jamón y pan y una pequeña cantidad de dinero en metálico, tras enterrar cerca de la laguna, dentro de una lata, la mayor parte del dinero ganado con sus derechos de autor. Para variar, tenía un aspecto bastante normal, vestida con una falda marrón de Sears Roebuck, una blusa blanca y zapatos planos. Los tenderos se afanaban en sus trabajos, atendían a los clientes, barrían la acera, mientras la miraban pasar.

Se detuvo en la esquina bajo la señal de Bus Stop y esperó hasta que el autobús de Trailways se detuvo ante ella con un siseo de los frenos de aire y le tapó el océano. Nadie bajó o subió cuando Kya dio un paso adelante y le compró al conductor un billete a Greenville. Preguntó por las fechas y horarios de regreso, y él le entregó una hoja con los datos y le guardó la maleta. Ella agarró con fuerza la mochila y subió al autobús. Y, antes de que le diera tiempo a pensar en ello, el autobús, que parecía tan largo como el pueblo, abandonó Barkley Cove.

Dos días después, a las 13.16, Kya bajó del Trailways que venía de Greenville. A esa hora había más gente en la calle, y la miraban y murmuraban mientras ella se echaba los largos cabellos por encima del hombro y le cogía la maleta al conductor. Cruzó la calle hasta el puerto, subió a su barca y se fue directa a casa. Habría querido decirle a Jumpin’ que había vuelto, como le había prometido, pero había más barcas haciendo cola para echar gasolina en su muelle y decidió dejarlo para el día siguiente. Además, así volvería antes con las gaviotas.

Por tanto, a la mañana siguiente, el 31 de octubre, al atracar en el muelle de Jumpin’ lo llamó y este salió de la pequeña tienda.

—Hola, Jumpin’, solo es para hacerte saber que he vuelto. Volví ayer.

Él no dijo nada mientras se acercaba a ella.

—Señorita Kya, yo… —dijo en cuanto la vio subir al muelle.

—¿Qué pasa? ¿Sucede algo? —repuso ella, e inclinó la cabeza.

Jumpin’ se la quedó mirando.

—Kya, ¿ha oído la noticia sobre el señor Chase?

—No. ¿Qué noticia?

—Chase Andrews ha muerto —soltó mientras negaba con la cabeza—. Murió en plena noche mientras usted estaba en Greenville.

—¿Qué?

Kya y Jumpin’ se miraron fijamente a los ojos.

—Lo encontraron ayer por la mañana bajo la vieja torre con un… Bueno, dicen que tenía el cuello roto y la cabeza destrozada. Creen que se cayó de lo alto.

Kya seguía boquiabierta.

—Es la comidilla del pueblo —continuó Jumpin’—. Algunos lo achacan a un accidente, pero se dice que el sheriff no está tan seguro. La madre de Chase está muy enfadada y dice que lo mataron. Hay mucho jaleo.

—¿Por qué creen que lo mataron…?

—Una de las rejas del suelo de la torre estaba levantada, él se cayó a plomo por ella, y eso les parece sospechoso. Hay quien dice que las rejas se dejan levantadas todo el tiempo porque los críos van a jugar allí, y que el señor Chase pudo caerse por accidente. Pero hay quien dice que lo asesinaron.

Kya guardaba silencio, así que Jumpin’ continuó.

—Uno de los motivos por los que lo dicen es que cuando encontraron al señor Chase no tenía el collar con la concha que lleva hace años, y su mujer dice que esa noche lo llevaba al salir de casa, antes de ir a cenar con sus padres. Dice que lo llevaba siempre.

A Kya se le secó la boca ante la mención del collar.

—Y, luego, los dos críos que encontraron a Chase, bueno, oyeron decir al sheriff que en el lugar no había huellas de pisadas. Ni una sola. Como si alguien hubiera borrado las pruebas. No paran de decirlo por todo el pueblo.

Jumpin’ le dijo cuándo sería el funeral, pero sabía que Kya no iría. Menudo espectáculo supondría para el círculo de costura y para el grupo de estudio de la Biblia. Y seguro que Kya estaría entre las especulaciones y cotilleos. «Gracias al Señor que estaba en Greenville a la hora de su muerte o ya le habrían echado la culpa», pensó Jumpin’.

Kya asintió a Jumpin’ y se fue a casa. Se detuvo en la embarrada orilla de la laguna y susurró unos versos de Amanda Hamilton.

Nunca subestimes

al corazón,

capaz de actos

que la mente no puede concebir.

El corazón dicta además de sentir.

¿Cómo, si no, podrías explicar

el camino que he tomado,

que tú has tomado,

el sendero que pasa por aquí?

Capítulo 49

Disfraces

1970

El siguiente testigo, un hombre de pelo blanco rizado vestido con un traje azul que brillaba de puro barato, se sentó en el banquillo tras declarar que su nombre era Larry Price y que conducía el autobús de Trailways por diferentes rutas de Carolina del Norte. A medida que Eric lo interrogaba, el señor Price confirmó que era posible viajar en autobús de Greenville a Barkley Cove y volver en la misma noche. También afirmó que condujo el autobús de Greenville a Barkley Cove la noche en que murió Chase y que ninguno de los pasajeros se parecía a la señorita Clark.

—Bueno, señor Price, ¿no le dijo usted al sheriff durante su investigación que en el autobús viajaba un hombre flaco que podía haber sido una mujer alta disfrazada de hombre? ¿Es así? Describa al pasajero, por favor.

—Sí, así es. Un joven blanco. Debía de medir cosa de metro setenta y cinco, y los pantalones le colgaban como sábanas de una valla. Llevaba una gorra grande y abultada, azul. Mantenía la cabeza gacha, no miraba a nadie.

—Y ahora que ha visto a la señorita Clark, ¿cree que es posible que el hombre flaco del autobús fuera la señorita Clark disfrazada? ¿Pudo llevar los cabellos ocultos bajo esa gorra?

—Sí, creo que sí.

Eric le pidió al juez que solicitara a Kya que se levantase, cosa que esta hizo con Tom Milton a su lado.

—Puede volver a sentarse, señorita Clark —dijo Eric, y luego se dirigió al testigo—: ¿Diría usted que el joven del autobús tenía la misma estatura que la señorita Clark?

—Yo diría que justo la misma —respondió el señor Price.

—Por tanto, si tenemos esto en cuenta, ¿diría usted que es probable que el hombre flaco que tomó el autobús de las 23.50 de Greenville a Barkley Cove la noche del 29 de octubre del año pasado fuera de hecho la acusada señorita Clark?

—Sí, yo diría que es muy posible.

—Gracias, señor Price. No hay más preguntas. Su testigo.

Tom se paró ante el banquillo de los testigos y, al cabo de cinco minutos de preguntas al señor Price, hizo un resumen.

—Lo que nos ha dicho usted es esto: uno, la noche del 29 de octubre de 1969, en el autobús de Greenville a Barkley Cove no viajaba ninguna mujer que se pareciera a la acusada; dos, en el autobús viajaba un hombre alto y delgado, pero en su momento, pese a verle la cara de cerca, no lo consideró una mujer disfrazada; tres, esta idea del disfraz se le ocurrió cuando se la sugirió el sheriff.

Tom continuó antes de que el testigo pudiera contestar.

—Señor Price, díganos cómo puede estar seguro de que ese hombre delgado tomó el autobús de las 23.50 el 29 de octubre. ¿Tomó nota acerca de ello, lo puso por escrito? Puede que fuera la noche anterior, o la siguiente. ¿Está usted seguro al cien por cien de que fue el 29 de octubre?

—Veo adónde quiere ir a parar. Cuando el sheriff me refrescaba la memoria, me pareció que ese hombre estuvo en el autobús, pero creo que ahora no estoy seguro al cien por cien.

—Además, señor Price, ¿no es cierto que el autobús se retrasó esa noche? De hecho, salió veinticinco minutos tarde, por lo que no llegó a Barkley Cove antes de la 1.40 de la madrugada. ¿Es eso correcto?

—Sí. —El señor Price miró a Eric—. Yo solo quiero ayudar, hacer lo que es debido.

Tom lo tranquilizó.

—Ha sido usted de gran ayuda, señor Price. Muchas gracias. No hay más preguntas.

Eric llamó a su siguiente testigo, el conductor del autobús de las 2.30 de Barkley Cove a Greenville en la madrugada del 30 de octubre, un tal John King. Testificó que la acusada, la señorita Clark, no iba en el autobús, pero sí una anciana…

—… tan alta como la señorita Clark, de pelo canoso, corto y rizado, como con permanente.

—Si mira a la acusada, señor King, ¿es posible que, de haberse disfrazado la señorita Clark de anciana, hubiera tenido un aspecto similar al de la mujer del autobús?

—Bueno, cuesta imaginarlo. Puede.

—Entonces, ¿es posible?

—Sí, supongo.

En el contrainterrogatorio, Tom dijo:

—La palabra «supongo» es inaceptable en un juicio por asesinato. ¿Vio usted a la acusada, la señorita Clark, en el autobús de las 2.30 de Barkley Cove a Greenville la madrugada del 30 de octubre de 1969?

—No, no la vi.

—¿Y hubo esa noche algún otro autobús de Barkley Cove a Greenville?

—No.

Capítulo 51

Luna menguante

1970

Por supuesto, el lenguaje del tribunal no era tan poético como el lenguaje de la marisma. Aun así, Kya veía semejanzas en su naturaleza. El juez, un macho alfa evidente, estaba seguro de su posición, por lo que su actitud era imponente, pero relajada y no amenazadora como la del jabalí territorial. Tom Milton también exudaba confianza y rango con su actitud y movimientos fluidos. Era un macho poderoso, aceptado como tal. El fiscal, por otra parte, dependía de corbatas anchas y coloridas y de chaquetas con hombreras para aumentar su estatus. Se hacía valer agitando los brazos o alzando la voz. Un macho inferior necesita gritar para que se fijen en él. El alguacil representaba el macho de nivel inferior, dependía de la cartuchera con reluciente pistola y agitaba el manojo de llaves y la aparatosa radio para reafirmar su posición. «Las jerarquías de dominación potencian la estabilidad en las poblaciones naturales, y en algunas menos naturales», pensó Kya.

El fiscal, con su corbata escarlata, pasó al frente y llamó a su siguiente testigo: Hal Miller, un hombre de veintiocho años, flaco como un palo, de revueltos cabellos castaños.

—Señor Miller, por favor, díganos dónde estaba usted y qué vio la noche del 29 al 30 de octubre de 1969 a la 1.45 horas.

—Allen Hunt y yo trabajábamos en el barco camaronero de Tim O’Neal, y volvíamos con retraso al puerto de Barkley Cove, cuando la vimos a ella, a la señorita Clark, en su barca, a cerca de una milla de distancia, al este de la bahía, en dirección nornoroeste.

—¿Adónde la conduciría ese rumbo?

—Directa a la cala que hay junto a la torre de vigilancia.

El juez Sims golpeó con el martillo ante el escándalo que se levantó y prolongó durante un minuto.

—¿No podría haber ido hacia otra parte?

—Bueno, supongo que sí, pero en esa dirección no hay nada más, aparte de kilómetros de bosque rodeado de pantanos. No conozco otro destino que la torre de vigilancia.

Los abanicos de las damas bombearon contra la calurosa e inquieta sala. Justicia dominical, dormido en el alféizar, se dejó caer al suelo y se acercó a Kya. Se frotó contra su pierna, por primera vez en la sala del tribunal, saltó a su regazo y se puso cómodo. Eric dejó de hablar y miró al juez, quizá planteándose una objeción por semejante despliegue de parcialidad, pero no había precedentes legales.

—¿Cómo puede estar seguro de que era la señorita Clark?

—Oh, todos conocemos su barca. Lleva años navegando en su barca.

—¿Llevaba luces en la barca?

—No, no llevaba. La habríamos arrollado de no verla.

—Pero ¿no es ilegal viajar en barca sin luces después de oscurecer?

—Sí, debería haber llevado luces. Pero no llevaba.

—Por tanto, la noche en que Chase Andrews murió en la torre de vigilancia, la señorita Clark viajaba en barca en esa dirección pocos minutos antes de la hora de su muerte. ¿Es eso correcto?

—Sí, eso fue lo que vimos.

Eric se sentó.

Tom caminó hacia el testigo.

—Buenos días, señor Miller.

—Buenos días.

—Señor Miller, ¿cuánto hace que es miembro de la tripulación del camaronero de Tim O’Neal?

—Ya hace tres años.

—Y dígame, por favor, ¿a qué hora salió la luna la noche del 29 al 30 de octubre?

—Era menguante, y no salió hasta después de que atracáramos en Barkley. En algún momento después de las dos, creo.

—Ya veo. Por tanto, no había luna cuando vio la barca cerca de Barkley Cove. Debía de estar muy oscuro.

—Sí. Estaba oscuro. Había luz de estrellas, pero sí, bastante oscuro.

—Por favor, ¿puede decirle al tribunal qué ropa llevaba la señorita Clark cuando pasó ante usted en su barca aquella noche?

—Bueno, no estábamos lo bastante cerca para ver qué llevaba puesto.

—¿Ah? No estaban lo bastante cerca para poder verle la ropa. —Tom miró al jurado mientras decía esto—. ¿A qué distancia estaban?

—Supongo que a unos buenos sesenta metros. Por lo menos.

—Sesenta metros. —Tom volvió a mirar al jurado—. Es una buena distancia para identificar una pequeña barca en la oscuridad. Dígame, señor Miller, ¿qué características, qué rasgos de la persona que iba en la barca le hicieron estar tan seguro de que era la señorita Clark?

—Bueno, como he dicho, casi todo el mundo en el pueblo conoce su barca, el aspecto que tiene de cerca y de lejos. Todos conocemos su barca y hemos visto su silueta en la proa, alta, delgada y eso. Es una silueta muy particular.

—Una silueta particular. Por tanto, cualquiera con esa misma forma, cualquier persona que fuese alta y delgada y viajara en ese tipo de barca se habría parecido a la señorita Clark. ¿Correcto?

—Supongo que podría haber alguna otra persona que se pareciera a ella, pero, al estar tanto en el mar, se acaban conociendo bien los barcos y a sus dueños, ¿sabe?

—Pero, señor Miller, debo recordarle que esto es un juicio por asesinato. La cosa no puede ser más seria, y en estos casos debemos estar seguros. No podemos atenernos a formas o siluetas vistas a sesenta metros en la oscuridad. Así que, por favor, dígale al tribunal si está usted seguro de que la persona que vio la noche del 29 al 30 de octubre de 1969 era la señorita Clark.

—Bueno, no, no puedo estar completamente seguro. Nunca dije que estuviera completamente seguro de que fuese ella. Pero estoy bastante…

—Eso es todo, señor Miller. Gracias.

—¿Repregunta, Eric? —preguntó el juez Sims.

—Hal, ha testificado que lleva viendo y reconociendo a la señorita Clark en su barca desde hace al menos tres años —señaló Eric desde su asiento—. Dígame, ¿alguna vez ha creído ver a la señorita Clark en la distancia y cuando se acercó resultó que no era ella? ¿Le ha pasado alguna vez?

—No, ninguna.

—¿Ninguna en tres años?

—Ninguna en tres años.

—El Estado ha concluido, su señoría.

Capítulo 52

El motel Tres Montañas

1970

El juez Sims entró en la sala y saludó a la mesa de la defensa.

—Señor Milton, ¿está listo para llamar al primer testigo de la defensa?

—Lo estoy, su señoría.

—Proceda.

—Por favor, diga su nombre y su profesión en Barkley Cove —dijo Tom una vez que la testigo prestó juramento y se sentó.

Kya alzó la mirada lo bastante para ver a la anciana bajita con su permanente de cabellos canos y púrpuras que años antes le había preguntado por qué iba siempre sola a la tienda. Puede que ahora fuese más bajita y llevara los rizos más apretados, pero tenía un aspecto sorprendentemente inmutable. La señora Singletary le había parecido una cotilla mandona, pero había sido ella quien le había regalado un silbato azul dentro de una media de Navidad el invierno siguiente a que mamá se fuera. Fue la única Navidad que tuvo Kya.

—Soy Sarah Singletary, dependienta en el Piggly Wiggly de Barkley Cove.

—Sarah, ¿es cierto que, desde su caja registradora en el Piggly Wiggly, ve usted la parada del autobús de Trailways?

—Sí, la veo con claridad.

—¿Vio usted a la acusada, la señorita Catherine Clark, esperando el autobús de las 14.30 el 28 de octubre del año pasado?

—Sí, vi a la señorita Clark esperando allí.

Tras decir esto, Sarah miró a Kya y recordó a la niña que había ido descalza a la tienda durante tantos años. Nadie lo sabría nunca, pero, antes de que la niña supiera contar, le daba de más en el cambio, un dinero que tenía que poner de su bolsillo para cuadrar la caja. Naturalmente, al manejarse Kya con cantidades pequeñas, Sarah la había ayudado con monedas de cinco centavos y otras monedas pequeñas, pero en algo la habría ayudado.

—¿Cuánto tiempo esperó? ¿La vio usted subir al autobús de las 14.30?

—Creo que esperó unos diez minutos. Todos la vimos comprar el billete al conductor, entregarle la maleta y subir al autobús. Cuando se alejó, ella iba dentro.

—Y creo que también la vio volver dos días después, el 30 de octubre, a las 13.16. ¿Es eso correcto?

—Sí, dos días después, poco después de las 13.15 de la tarde, alcé la vista cuando paró el autobús y la señorita Clark bajó de él. Se la señalé a las otras dependientas.

—¿Y qué hizo luego?

—Ella fue andando hasta el muelle, subió a su barca y se dirigió al sur.

—Gracias, Sarah. Eso es todo.

—¿Alguna pregunta, Eric? —preguntó el juez.

—No, su señoría, no tengo preguntas. De hecho, por la lista de testigos, veo que la defensa pretende llamar a varios ciudadanos para que testifiquen que la señorita Clark subió y bajó del autobús de Trailways en las fechas y horas que ha declarado la señora Singletary. La acusación no refuta este testimonio. De hecho, sostenemos que la señorita Clark viajó en esos autobuses a esas horas y, con la venia de la corte, no consideramos necesario que lo afirmen así más testigos.

—Muy bien. Señora Singletary, queda excusada. ¿Y usted, señor Milton? Si la acusación acepta el hecho de que la señorita Clark subió al autobús de las 14.30 el 28 de octubre de 1969 y que volvió alrededor de las 13.16 el 30 de octubre de 1969, ¿necesita llamar a más testigos a tal efecto?

—No, su señoría.

Su expresión aparentaba calma, pero Tom maldecía por dentro. La coartada de Kya de que había estado lejos del pueblo la hora en que murió Chase era el principal argumento de la defensa. Pero Eric había conseguido diluir la coartada al aceptarla, al afirmar que no necesitaba oír más testimonios sobre el viaje de ida y vuelta de Kya a Greenville en esas fechas. No afectaba a la acusación, dado que esta afirmaba que Kya había vuelto de noche a Barkley para cometer el asesinato. Tom tenía previsto el riesgo, pero había considerado crucial que el jurado oyese esos testimonios y visualizara a Kya saliendo del pueblo a la luz del día para no volver hasta después del incidente. Ahora pensarían que su coartada no era lo bastante importante para que fuera necesario comprobarla.

—Entendido. Por favor, proceda con el siguiente testigo.

Calvo y quisquilloso, con la chaqueta abotonada y tensa contra un vientre redondo, el señor Lang Furlough testificó que poseía y dirigía el motel Tres Montañas de Greenville y que la señorita Clark se había alojado en él del 28 al 30 de octubre de 1969.

Kya detestaba escuchar a ese hombre de pelo grasiento, al que creía que no volvería a ver, y ahí estaba, hablando de ella como si ella no estuviera. Explicó cómo le enseñó la habitación del motel, pero no mencionó que había tardado en irse y que no paraba de inventar razones para quedarse hasta que ella le señaló la puerta para indicarle que se fuera. Cuando Tom le preguntó cómo podía estar seguro de las idas y venidas de la señorita Clark en el hotel, soltó una risita y dijo que era el tipo de mujer en el que se fijan los hombres. Añadió lo rara que era por no saber usar el teléfono y por ir andando desde la estación de autobuses con una maleta de cartón y en ella su cena preparada.

—Señor Furlough, la noche siguiente, es decir, la del 29 de octubre de 1969, la noche en que murió Chase Andrews, pasó usted toda la noche en el mostrador de recepción. ¿Es eso correcto?

—Sí.

—Después de que la señorita Clark volviera a su habitación a las diez de la noche, tras cenar con su editor, ¿la vio salir de nuevo? ¿La vio salir o regresar a su habitación en algún momento de la noche del 29 de octubre o a primera hora del 30 de octubre?

—No. Estuve allí toda la noche y no la vi salir. Como he dicho, su habitación estaba justo frente al mostrador de recepción, así que la habría visto.

—Gracias, señor Furlough, eso es todo. Su testigo.

Tras varios minutos de contrainterrogatorio, Eric continuó:

—Bueno, señor Furlough, de momento lo tenemos dejando la zona de recepción para ir dos veces a su apartamento, ir al baño y volver; al repartidor de pizzas llevándole una pizza, a usted pagándole y etcétera; cuatro clientes registrándose, dos yéndose, y todo ello mientras usted terminaba de contabilizar los recibos. Yo diría, señor Furlough, que durante ese jaleo hubo muchas ocasiones en las que la señorita Clark pudo haber salido discretamente de su habitación y cruzar rápidamente la calle sin que usted la viera. ¿No es eso posible?

—Bueno, supongo que sí. Pero no vi nada. Lo que yo digo es que esa noche no la vi salir de la habitación.

—Lo entiendo, señor Furlough. Y lo que yo digo es que es muy posible que la señorita Clark saliera de su habitación, fuese andando a la estación de autobuses, viajara en uno hasta Barkley Cove, asesinara a Chase Andrews y volviese a su habitación sin que usted la viera por estar muy ocupado con su trabajo. No hay más preguntas.

Scupper entró en el tribunal después del descanso para almorzar, cuando todo el mundo se hubo sentado y el juez tomó asiento. Tate se volvió para ver a su padre entrando por el pasillo, todavía con el mono y las botas amarillas de pescador. Scupper no había asistido al juicio alegando motivos de trabajo, pero sobre todo porque le confundía la larga relación que su hijo tenía con la señorita Clark. Era como si Tate nunca hubiera albergado sentimientos por otra chica y no hubiera dejado de querer a esa misteriosa mujer ni siquiera de adulto, cuando ya era un profesional. Una mujer a la que ahora acusaban de asesinato.

Ese mediodía, en su barco, rodeado de redes, Scupper había respirado hondo. Su rostro se había encendido por la vergüenza al darse cuenta de que él también, como algunos de esos ignorantes pueblerinos, había sido presa de los prejuicios porque Kya se había criado en la marisma. Recordaba cómo Tate le había enseñado orgulloso el primer libro de Kya sobre conchas y que él mismo se había quedado pasmado ante semejante proeza científica y artística. Se había comprado un ejemplar de cada uno de sus libros sin mencionárselo a Tate. Era ridículo.

Estaba muy orgulloso de su hijo, de cómo había sabido siempre lo que quería y cómo conseguirlo. Y Kya había hecho lo mismo que él, aun cuando tenía muchas cosas en contra.

¿Cómo podía dejar de ponerse del lado de Tate? Nada era más importante que apoyar a su hijo. Soltó la red, que cayó a sus pies, dejó el barco oscilando contra el muelle y fue directo al tribunal.

Al llegar a la primera fila, Jodie, Jumpin’ y Mabel se levantaron para dejarle pasar y que se sentara junto a Tate. Padre e hijo asintieron el uno al otro y las lágrimas se amontonaron en los ojos de Tate.

Tom Milton esperó a que Scupper se sentara y el silencio en la sala fuera completo.

—Su señoría, la defensa llama a Robert Foster.

El señor Foster era delgado, de estatura media, con una barba recortada y ojos amables. Vestía una chaqueta de tweed, corbata y pantalones caqui. Tom le preguntó su nombre y profesión.

—Me llamo Robert Foster, y soy editor en la Harrison Morris Publishing Company, de Boston, Massachusetts.

Kya miraba al suelo con la mano apoyada en la frente. Su editor era la única persona a la que conocía que no la consideraba la Chica Salvaje, que la respetaba e incluso parecía intimidado por sus conocimientos y talento. Y ahora estaba en un tribunal, la veía en la mesa de la defensa, acusada de asesinato.

—¿Es usted el editor de los libros de la señorita Catherine Clark?

—Sí, lo soy. Es una naturalista, artista y escritora de mucho talento. Una de nuestras autoras preferidas.

—¿Puede confirmarnos si viajó a Greenville, Carolina del Norte, el 29 de octubre de 1969, y que se reunió con la señorita Clark tanto el día 29 como el 30?

—Así es. Debía asistir a una conferencia y, puesto que sabía que me sobraría tiempo cuando estuviera en la ciudad, pero no suficiente para viajar hasta su casa, invité a la señorita Clark a Greenville para que pudiéramos vernos.

—¿Puede decirnos la hora exacta en la que usted la acompañó a su motel la noche del 29 de octubre del año pasado?

—Tras nuestra reunión, cenamos en el hotel y acompañé a Kya a su motel a las 21.55 horas.

Kya recordaba cómo esperó en el umbral del comedor, lleno de mesas iluminadas con velas bajo la suave luz de los candelabros. Copas altas de vino sobre manteles blancos. Comensales elegantemente vestidos que conversaban en voz baja, mientras que ella llevaba una falda a cuadros y una blusa. Robert y ella cenaron trucha de Carolina del Norte con crocanti de almendras, arroz silvestre, crema de espinacas y rollitos de levadura. Kya se sintió muy a gusto mientras él conducía la conversación con cómoda elegancia, y se limitaba a temas sobre naturaleza que le eran familiares.

Al recordarlo, se sintió asombrada de cómo lo había llevado. Pero la verdad era que el restaurante, con todo su esplendor, no era tan grandioso como su pícnic favorito. Cuando tenía quince años, Tate había ido un amanecer a su cabaña y, tras rodearle los hombros con una manta, viajaron tierra adentro por un laberinto de canales hasta un bosque que nunca había visto. Luego caminaron un kilómetro y medio hasta el linde de un prado anegado donde la hierba fresca brotaba a través del cieno, y allí colocaron la manta bajo helechos altos como paraguas.

—Y ahora esperaremos —dijo mientras servía té de un termo y le ofrecía «bolas de mapache», una mezcla horneada de masa de pan, salchicha picante y queso cheddar que había preparado para la ocasión. Incluso en ese frío tribunal recordaba la calidez de los hombros de Tate al tocar los de ella bajo la manta, mientras mordisqueaban y bebían el desayuno del pícnic.

No tuvieron que esperar mucho. Momentos después, se oyó por el norte un alboroto que sonó como un cañonazo.

—Ya vienen —había anunciado Tate.

En el horizonte apareció una fina nube negra que se elevaba a los cielos a medida que se acercaba. Los chillidos aumentaron en intensidad y volumen a medida que la nube llenaba rápidamente el cielo hasta no dejar un resquicio de azul. Cientos de miles de gansos nivales, que aleteaban, graznaban y planeaban, cubrieron el mundo. Masas arremolinadas giraron y descendieron para aterrizar. Quizá medio millón de alas se movieron al unísono mientras patas rosas anaranjadas descendían y una borrasca de aves se acercaba. Primero un ganso tras otro, luego de diez en diez y, finalmente, a centenares, aterrizaron a unos metros de Kya y Tate, sentados bajo los helechos. El cielo se vació mientras el húmedo prado se cubría de la nieve que caía.

Ningún salón elegante era comparable a eso, y las bolas de mapache habían tenido más sabor y lustre que la trucha con crocanti de almendras.

—¿Vio a la señorita Clark entrar en su habitación?

—Por supuesto. Le abrí la puerta y esperé a que entrase antes de irme.

—¿Vio a la señorita Clark al día siguiente?

—Habíamos quedado para desayunar, así que la recogí a las 7.30 de la mañana. Comimos en la casa de las tortitas Stack ‘Em High. La llevé de vuelta al motel a las 9.00. Y esa fue la última vez que la vi antes de hoy.

Miró a Kya, pero ella bajó la mirada.

—Gracias, señor Foster. No tengo más preguntas.

Eric se levantó para intervenir.

—Señor Foster, me preguntaba por qué se alojó usted en el hotel Piedmont, que es el mejor hotel de la ciudad, mientras que su editorial alojaba a la señorita Clark, una de sus autoras preferidas y de más talento, como usted mismo ha dicho, en un motel tan corriente como el Tres Montañas.

—Por supuesto, ofrecimos, e incluso recomendamos, a la señorita Clark que se alojara en el Piedmont, pero ella insistió en quedarse en el motel.

—¿De verdad? ¿Conocía ella el nombre del motel? ¿Solicitó específicamente alojarse en el Tres Montañas?

—Sí, nos escribió diciendo que prefería quedarse en el Tres Montañas.

—¿Dijo por qué?

—No, no sé por qué.

—Pues yo tengo una idea. Este es un mapa turístico de Greenville. —Eric agitó un mapa mientras se acercaba al banquillo de los testigos—. Como puede ver aquí, señor Foster, el hotel Piedmont, el hotel de cuatro estrellas que usted ofreció a la señorita Clark, está situado en la zona del centro. En cambio, el Tres Montañas está en la autopista 258, cerca de la estación de autobuses Trailways. De hecho, si estudia este mapa como he hecho yo, verá que el Tres Montañas es el motel más cercano a la estación de autobuses…

—Objeción, su señoría —dijo Tom—. El señor Foster no es una autoridad en la ciudad de Greenville.

—No, pero el mapa sí. Veo adónde quiere llegar, Eric, y lo permitiré. Proceda.

—Señor Foster, si alguien planeara hacer un viaje rápido a la estación de autobuses en plena noche, es lógico que prefiriera el Tres Montañas al Piedmont. Sobre todo, si pensaba hacerlo a pie. Lo único que necesito es su confirmación de que la señorita Clark solicitó específicamente alojarse en el Tres Montañas y no en el Piedmont.

—Como he dicho, ella solicitó el Tres Montañas.

—No tengo más preguntas.

—¿Repregunta? —consultó el juez Sims.

—Sí, su señoría. Señor Foster, ¿cuántos años hace que trabaja con la señorita Clark?

—Tres años.

—Y, pese a no conocerla en persona hasta su visita a Greenville del pasado octubre, ¿diría usted que ha llegado a conocer a la señorita Clark mediante su correspondencia de estos tres años? En ese caso, ¿querría describirla?

—Sí, así es. Creo que es una persona tímida y amable. Prefiere vivir sola en el bosque; me llevó un tiempo convencerla para que viniera a Greenville. No le gustan las multitudes.

—¿Multitudes como las que encontraría en un hotel tan grande como el Piedmont?

—Sí.

—De hecho, ¿no diría usted, señor Foster, que no le sorprendió que la señorita Clark, a quien le gusta la soledad, prefiriera un motel pequeño y un tanto remoto a un hotel grande y ajetreado en el centro de la ciudad? ¿Que esa elección casa con su persona?

—Sí, yo diría que sí…

—¿Y no le parece también lógico que la señorita Clark, que no está familiarizada con el transporte público y sabía que tendría que ir caminando de la estación de autobuses a su hotel y vuelta, llevando una maleta, eligiera un hotel o motel cerca de la estación?

—Sí.

—Gracias. Es todo.

Robert Foster dejó el banquillo de los testigos y se sentó detrás de Kya, junto a Tate, Scupper, Jodie, Jumpin’ y Mabel.

Esa tarde, Tom volvió a llamar como testigo al sheriff.

Por la lista de testigos, Kya sabía que no quedaban muchos, y la idea la enfermaba. Después vendrían los alegatos finales y luego el veredicto. Mientras una oleada de testigos la apoyara, podía aspirar a la absolución o al menos a retrasar la condena. No habría veredicto si el juicio se eternizaba. Intentó centrar su mente en campos de gansos nivales, como había hecho desde que empezó el juicio, pero solo veía imágenes de cárceles, barrotes, pegajosas paredes de cemento. Ocasionales insertos mentales de una silla eléctrica. Y muchas correas.

De pronto, sintió que no podía respirar, que no podía seguir allí sentada por más tiempo, que la cabeza le pesaba demasiado para levantarla. Se desplomó ligeramente y, cuando tuvo que apoyar la cabeza en las manos, Tom se apartó del sheriff y corrió a su lado.

—Su señoría, solicito un breve receso. La señorita Clark necesita un descanso.

—Concedido. El jurado queda excusado durante un receso de quince minutos.

Tom la ayudó a levantarse y la acompañó por una puerta lateral hasta una pequeña sala de conferencias, donde se desplomó en una silla.

—¿Qué tiene, Kya? ¿Qué le pasa? —dijo él mientras se sentaba a su lado.

Ella enterró la cabeza en las manos.

—¿Cómo puede preguntarme esto? ¿No es evidente? ¿Cómo se puede soportar esto? Me encuentro demasiado enferma, demasiado cansada de estar allí sentada. ¿Tengo que seguir haciéndolo? ¿No puede seguir el juicio sin mí?

De lo único que era capaz, lo único que quería, era volver a su celda y acurrucarse con Justicia dominical.

—No, me temo que no. En un caso como este, la ley requiere su presencia.

—¿Y si no puedo? ¿Y si me niego? Lo único que podrían hacer es meterme en la cárcel.

—Kya, es la ley. Tiene que asistir, y, de todos modos, es mejor que esté presente. A un jurado le resulta más fácil condenar a un acusado ausente. Pero no será durante mucho más tiempo, Kya.

—Eso no hace que me sienta mejor, ¿no lo ve? Lo que venga ahora será mucho peor.

—Eso no lo sabemos. No olvide que si la cosa no sale como queremos, podremos apelar.

Kya no respondió. La idea de una apelación la enfermaba aún más. El paseo forzoso por diferentes tribunales, alejarse más y más de las marismas. Probablemente por pueblos más grandes. Por un cielo sin gaviotas. Tom salió de la sala y volvió con un vaso de té helado y una bolsa de cacahuetes salados. Bebió el té, pero rechazó lo otro. Unos minutos después, el alguacil llamó a la puerta y los llevó de vuelta a la sala del tribunal. La mente de Kya entraba y salía de la realidad, y captaba retazos del testimonio.

—Sheriff Jackson —dijo Tom—, la acusación afirma que la señorita Clark salió esa noche a escondidas de su motel y fue a pie desde el motel Tres Montañas a la estación de autobuses, un viaje de al menos veinte minutos. Que entonces tomó el autobús de las 23.50 de Greenville a Barkley Cove, pero el autobús salió tarde, así que no pudo llegar a Barkley hasta la 1.40 de la madrugada. Afirma que desde la parada de autobús de Barkley fue andando hasta el muelle, tres o cuatro minutos; luego viajó en barca hasta la cala de la torre de vigilancia, al menos veinte minutos; caminó hasta la torre, otros ocho minutos; subió en la oscuridad, pongamos cuatro o cinco minutos al menos; levantó la reja, unos pocos segundos; esperó a Chase un tiempo indefinido y luego hizo el recorrido a la inversa.

»Todo esto debió de ocuparle un mínimo de una hora siete minutos, sin contar el tiempo que se supone que debió de esperar a Chase. Pero el autobús de vuelta a Greenville, que debía tomar, salió cincuenta minutos después de su llegada. Por tanto, los hechos son simples: no tuvo tiempo para cometer este supuesto crimen. ¿No es eso correcto, sheriff?

—Le habría ido muy justo, cierto. Pero podría haber corrido de la barca a la torre y a la vuelta; pudo recortar algún minuto aquí o allí.

—No basta con un minuto aquí o allí. Habría necesitado veinte minutos extra. Por lo menos. ¿Cómo podría haberse ahorrado veinte minutos?

—Bueno, puede que no fuera en barca; puede que fuese andando o corriendo desde la parada de autobús, por el sendero de arena hasta la torre. Habría sido mucho más rápido que yendo por mar.

Desde la mesa de la fiscalía, Eric Chastain miraba con furia al sheriff. Había convencido al jurado de que Kya había tenido tiempo para cometer el crimen y volver al autobús. No le había resultado muy complicado. Tenía un testigo importante, el camaronero, que había testificado que vio a la señorita Clark dirigiéndose a la torre en barca.

—¿Tiene alguna prueba de que la señorita Clark fuese a la torre por tierra, sheriff?

—No. Pero lo de que fuera por tierra es una buena teoría.

—¡Teoría! —Tom se volvió hacia el jurado—. El tiempo de las teorías ya ha quedado atrás, antes de que usted arrestara a la señorita Clark, antes de que la retuviera en la cárcel dos meses. El hecho es que no puede probar que fuese por tierra, y que no tuvo tiempo suficiente para hacerlo por mar. No hay más preguntas.

Eric se enfrentó al sheriff para el contrainterrogatorio.

—Sheriff, ¿es cierto que las aguas próximas a Barkley Cove son presa de fuertes corrientes, remolinos y resacas que pueden influir en la velocidad de una barca?

—Sí, es cierto. Lo sabemos todos los que vivimos aquí.

—Alguien que supiera aprovechar esas corrientes podría viajar con mucha rapidez en barca desde el muelle hasta la torre. En tal caso, resultaría factible ganarle veinte minutos al recorrido. ¿Es eso correcto?

Eric estaba molesto de que se hubiera sugerido otra teoría, necesitaba ofrecer algo plausible a lo que pudieran agarrarse los miembros del jurado que le siguieran.

—Sí, es correcto.

—Gracias.

En cuanto Eric se apartó del banquillo de los testigos, Tom se levantó para repreguntar.

—Sí o no, sheriff, ¿tiene alguna prueba de que la noche del 29 al 30 de octubre hubiera alguna corriente, remolino o fuerte viento que pudiese reducir el tiempo de navegación a alguien que viajase desde el puerto de Barkley Cove a la torre de vigilancia, o alguna prueba de que la señorita Clark hubiera ido por tierra hasta la torre?

—No, pero estoy seguro de que…

—Sheriff, no me importa de lo que pueda estar seguro o no. ¿Tiene alguna prueba de que hubiese fuertes corrientes en la noche del 29 de octubre de 1969?

—No, no la tengo.

Chapter 55
Memory transcription subject:

Captain Kalsim,
Krakotl Alliance Command

Date [standardized human time]:
October 18, 2136

Darkness had fallen over the reserve, when I peeked out from the tent. Sleep had instilled new energy in my veins. There was a slim hope of escaping Earth, if we could keep away from human search parties. Our posse needed to figure out our next move, and how to transport the predator kid without harming it.

A muffled whine echoed from behind me. I twisted around to see Arjun, bound in tight rope from head to toe. It must've woken before me, and been struggling to break free. Several layers of tape had been slapped over its mouth, wasting medical gauze. I assumed Zarn didn't want to hear a human speak.

Swallowing my nerves, I approached it. "Shh, it's okay. I'm going to have to rip the tape off. Close your eyes."

How could Doctor Zarn treat it like a thoughtless animal? Predators or not, humans were feeling sapients. The level of bindings was both excessive and unnecessary. Something as simple as tying a bell around its leg would suffice; it didn't seem fast or stealthy.

The predator child squeezed its eyes shut. I yanked the adhesive off as quickly as I could, and winced at the grimace on its features. The skin by its lip carried a red patch behind. The creature refrained from biting me with its slobbery canines, which was a relief.

I set to work untangling the series of knots. What happened if Arjun tried to take me by surprise, once it was loose? It could go for my gun before I knew what hit me. I was within grappling distance, and its reflexes must be quicker than mine.

The last of the rope came untangled, and the human wriggled out of its entrapments. My gaze drifted to my sidearm. I took a few steps back, and barely resisted the urge to draw a weapon. The kid had faced enough hardship these past few days; it needed someone to be civilized to it.

The watery look in its eyes…the poor thing is terrified. There's no question these wretches have feelings.

"I'm sorry that they did that to you, Arjun. Are you okay?" I asked gently.

It sniffled. "The only reason you're not killing me is because you think they'll trade resources for me. I heard how you talked about me."

"That stopped Zarn and Jala from shooting you, didn't it? I would've let you go. Trust me, I want to get you back to your family safely."

"That's bullshit! Those two aliens are evil. If you want me released, then help me get out of here!"

I was beginning to regret taking the tape off this thing's mouth. That combative shouting wasn't helping anyone. It needed to keep its voice down, or Zarn would realize I was trying to console a human. However, expecting an aggressive predator to keep its head was a bit overambitious. Holding this child to Krakotl sensibility standards would be unfair.

"I need the doctor cooperating." My feathers puffed out with irritation. "My friend with the bandages will die without him. He's a good person…smart, witty."

The predator bared its teeth. "None of you are good people. You killed millions indiscriminately, and you liked it."

"You don't know what you're talking about. I had to choose between hundreds of civilizations and yours. It was a terrible decision, but a necessity for the continuance of life. Every step of the way, I tried to minimize human suffering."

"By dropping bombs on cities? Do you hear yourself?"

"To the very last moment we approached Earth, I was trying to think of another way. My own crew hates that I treat your kind with dignity, and that I offer predators surrender."

"Then your crew are assholes."

Arjun's voice sounded hoarse, and its lips looked dry. How had Zarn expected it to drink water with its mouth taped shut? The Takkan doctor hadn't even left rations nearby. It probably would make that hateful "expert" giddy if it died of dehydration.

I fished through my own rations, making sure never to turn my back on the human. It would be foolish to leave myself vulnerable to pouncing or strangulation. The child watched with interest as I procured a canteen. It gulped down a bit more than I'd like, before handing the canister back.

"Jala is the other Krakotl you saw. Her brain doesn't feel empathy or fear," I said. "She can't help that she's vicious, any more than you can."

In fact, Arjun is much more capable of compassion. It has tried to appeal to my morality several times. It cares for more than its own life.

The beast scowled. "Humans are not vicious. You're brainwashed, Kalsim! We have lives, families, schools…jokes, songs, and games, just like you."

"I am sorry for all the beauty you've lost, but that doesn't change the truth. Tell me that you can't see humans killing or enslaving weaker cultures. That you wouldn't happily take our worlds away, and reduce us to playthings."

"What? That's not our plan. We would never do that."

"Yet you've done these things to your own kind. And we are alien, not human. You'll build your empire off our backs, one way or another. It's in your DNA, passed from your ancestors to little ones like you. That…your growth is the threat."

Arjun clenched its fists in indignation, but was distracted by its stomach growling. Racking my brain, I tried to recall what Noah shared about human needs. The speaker claimed that their diet was primarily vegetation, and that they could live without meat. That meant this adolescent could consume our food without issue.

My talons retrieved a slab of dried tree bark. "Here. Stop arguing with me and eat this."

"Um, that doesn't look like my food." Arjun eyed the offering suspiciously. It took a hesitant nibble, then spit the bite out. "That is bitter…gross!"

"I'm giving you my rations so you don't starve. It doesn't have to taste like your delectable, blood-filled cuisine."

The kid made a disgusted face, but swallowed several bites. The gagging sound it made seemed rather dramatic. You'd think it was expelling its lungs, or that I had fed it a corrosive poison. This ruckus was going to ensure Zarn and Jala checked on us.

Few Krakotl would've gone out of their way to ensure a predator's welfare. Arjun didn't understand why its planet was attacked, but I didn't blame it for that. It was emotionally distressed, and unable to see these matters with objectivity. Maybe the youth would come to know that I protected it, in time.

The Takkan doctor sauntered in, wielding a pistol. "Good grief, Kalsim. You've let it loose, and you're feeding it?"

"Tree bark. We don't want it to lose its mind and gorge on Thyon's corpse," I said. "Speaking of which, where is the first officer?"

"Don't change the fucking subject. So now, instead of being bartered for supplies, this human is using up precious resources and manpower?"

"It's a temporary loss. We don't want to offer up the kid as a walking skeleton."

"Why the hell not? If you keep its stomach empty, the humans will be under more of a time constraint to get it back. That's assuming predators care at all."

Arjun shoved the last of the bark in its mouth, inching away from Zarn. Its cheeks were tear-stained, but absolute hatred shone in its pupils as well. I couldn't imagine how overwhelming the predatory chemicals flowing through its veins were. The doctor's lack of compassion was staggering; with how cold his suggestion of starvation was, you would think he had Jala's disorder.

I fixed the Takkan with a glare. "First off, we would encourage the humans to treat us the same in kind. This predator doesn't deserve to suffer for existing. It has suffered enough pain and heartache today."

The physician swished his tail. "You're oh-so-worried about its feigned emotions. Why do you care what it feels?"

"Fuck you! I'm not an it," the human growled.

Zarn charged the kid, rearing back with his firearm. The doctor trembled with anger, as he swung the gun toward its head. The predator's binocular gaze widened in alarm. I couldn't let it be beaten to a pulp for speaking its mind, when all it had done was complain about our language.

Arjun had a family and a future out there, which was jeopardized by the Takkan's malice. The more I considered our conversation, its intelligence was impressive for a child. Granted, it would help propagate the survival of the human race. But that seemed a likely probability no matter what, so what did harming it achieve?

I don't want to see it in pain…or worse, end up like Thyon.

Without realizing I had moved, I stretched my wing in the strike's path. Zarn was committed to the blow by the time I obstructed his angle. The metal gun connected with my soft tissue, while the human cowered behind a feathery shield. Pain flared down my left appendage, resonating to the bone. The throbbing sensation was nauseating, and a single glance told me it was broken.

"Shit! You broke my wing," I screeched, doubling over in anguish. "What if that had been Arjun's head? You could've cracked his skull!"

The doctor leveled his gun barrel at me. "His?"

My eyes widened, as I realized my slip of the tongue. I shook my head, trying to filter away any positive assessments of Arjun. The kid was lying prone on the floor, and its eyes were bulging. If their tools and pack were taken away, humans weren't competent predators. I was the only one that could protect this beast.

Zarn's concentration waned, as a squawking Jala landed behind him. I took the opportunity to wrench the gun from his grip with my good wing. Ironically, I could use his services to patch the broken bone up. The pain intensified with the slightest movements or vibrations; the Takkan hadn't even flinched at assaulting me.

I brandished the firearm awkwardly. "Mutiny is punishable by death, unless the captain is deemed unfit for command. Why shouldn't I carry out your sentence?"

"Kalsim, p-put the gun down," the doctor stammered. "You're being unreasonable."

"I am unreasonable?! Then what on Nishtal do I call you?"

Jala issued a hearty laugh. "What did I miss?"

The female Krakotl's eyes darted behind him, and she drew her own firearm. Arjun had capitalized on the chaos, making a break for the exit. The human skidded to a halt, once the armed sociopath blocked its path. After witnessing how slippery Terran forces were, I really should've been paying more attention to it.

I hope Jala doesn't make any hasty decisions here.

"Zarn proved himself a threat to crew safety and this mission." I lowered the pistol, and noted the contempt in the doctor's eyes. "But he's not going to disobey orders again, is he?"

The Takkan sighed. "No…sir."

"Your wing isn't supposed to bend like that, Kalsim," Jala chuckled.

I struggled to ignore the searing pain. "Tell me something I don't know…ah, go on, laugh at my misfortune later. Is there something you need?"

"I circled the perimeter from the skies, and spotted a human a few clicks away. It's heading toward our position…and it's armed."

Arjun mustered a feral snarl. "Dad."

Panic swelled in my chest, at the thought of Terrans converging on our position. Confronting Arjun's father was an option, but we didn't know that it was alone. The 'photographer' might notice that something was wrong, and alert authorities. Humans were dangerous without the element of surprise; it was unclear whether our small posse could survive direct combat.

It would be in our best interest to leave the kid, and that was what my conscience demanded. However, that plan wouldn't be popular with my companions. With a crippled wing, taking on Jala and Zarn was an incredible risk. Both could aim guns without difficulty, and a flightworthy Krakotl could maneuver freely.

More importantly, the doctor's incapacitation would damn Thyon. That was the main reason I couldn't punish this mutiny. The Farsul's life took precedence over Arjun's welfare, plain and simple. I had to keep this together until Thyon regained consciousness.

"It's time to move," I decided. "Where is your patient, Zarn?"

The doctor scowled. "Thyon is safe. Jala crafted a pulley system, and put him up in a nearby tree. Predators won't get to him there, though I can't speak for humans finding him."

"Good. We need to hurry, before dozens of full-grown beasts descend on us. We'll come back as soon as human activity cools off."

Jala began collecting our supplies, as well as anything Arjun had that was useful. I steered the kid out into the open, trying to be gentle with my gun prodding. Intimidating it wasn't my desire, but we needed to move quickly. There was no time for a diplomatic approach.

Arjun looked around in desperation, as we staggered out of the encampment. I knew it wanted to be rescued. That pleading gaze reminded me of the burning pups, praying to be saved from their extermination. Why did it have to jog up those memories, with every expression? I thought I was past that guilt.

"DAD! HELP!" the kid screamed. "They're—"

I clapped my good wing over its mouth. "You idiot! Are you trying to get yourself killed?"

Zarn passed me a roll of medical gauze, a conceited glint in his eyes. I could hear the words 'told you so' from the smug doctor. He scowled at the human, tracing a toe over his own throat slowly. The child swallowed, and I suppose it understood the gesture.

I applied a single layer of tape, and offered a sympathetic pat. The predator hadn't left much choice other than to gag it. Not only could that wailing cry have alerted its father, but it could've drawn attention from forest beasts.

That squashed all hopes of Arjun's guardian accepting the disappearance as a tragic accident. Its suspicions were going to be elevated, and its protective instincts would seek answers. Our entourage was about to find out exactly how good humans were at tracking.

⋯ ✧ ⋯ ✧ ⋯

Chapter 57
Memory transcription subject:

Slanek,
Venlil Space Corps

Date [standardized human time]:
October 18, 2136

Marcel leaned over the destroyer’s railing, allowing the saltwater to splash his face. The predator’s eyes stared where the towering skyline of New York City had once been. His loved ones were in one of the nearby bunkers, perhaps buried beneath a mountain of rubble. The human resolved to search for Nulia and Lucy, but I feared his reaction if they weren’t found alive.

The American military sent most available service members to the remnants of its largest city, once the environment was deemed safe. Rescue prospects weren’t promising for the main hubs, so efforts would be focused on the city outskirts. With the traditional naval ports and space docking sites pulverized, the boat would allow alien visitors to touch down.

My skin crawled at the thought of the Arxur landing on Earth. I remembered what the grays had done on the bombed-out cradle; it terrified me that they might get a taste for human flesh. What if the survivors, like Marcel, were rounded up onto a cattle ship? The thought of him being caged or tortured again filled me with despair.

Minutes from now, those monsters were going to be walking onto this very deck. I couldn’t stop focusing on that image; every instinct compelled me to hurl myself overboard. The Terrans were in no condition to protect me. I didn’t believe for a second that those emotionless predators were genuinely here to help.

The red-haired human studied his reflection in the water. “Shit. Do you remember the first time we chatted online, Slanek?”

“You said, ‘Hello.’ I sat at my keyboard for two hours, trying to envision your true intent,” I muttered. “I was terrified to talk to a predator.”

“Wait, that’s why you didn’t answer right away? I mean, I was nervous too, but more about fucking up first contact.”

“Marc, all I could think was, what have I done? After several bouts of crying, multiple drafted messages to Republic emergency services to drop out of the program…”

“You asked me, with no context or greeting, what I saw when I looked in the mirror.”

Marcel didn’t finish the anecdote, instead tilting his head in consideration. At the time, the human answered, A mouth, a nose, two eyes and ears. I’d be concerned if that changed. The horrors of my imagination evaporated with laughter. I felt guilty that I had been so preoccupied with his appearance in the beginning.

The worry creases on his forehead aged him by a decade, as did the blemish of the scars on his cheek. By comparison, my friend’s paralyzing gaze had been full of life, with that snarl he couldn’t contain. I wanted to remember the humans as that optimistic race; affectionate and carefree. Whatever compromises our beloved predators had to make, I wouldn’t let them change my perspective.

“I see a survivor.” Swallowing my nerves, I propped myself over the railing. My gray fur was a matted mess, and my slender ears were pinned in terror. “T-two of them, actually. Please, don’t let the Arxur eat me.”

He ruffled the stray tuft on my head. “I’m scared too, buddy. I have nightmares about them eating that immobilized Gojid…then, eating you or Nulia. Is it wrong to admit that?”

“No. Your f-feelings are important too. You’re just really good at acting strong.”

“Key word, acting.”

An angular craft rocketed down from the cloud cover, and I squeezed my tail around the human’s wrist. The curvature of the ship’s belly suggested it was stocked with missiles; it was brimming with weaponry from every angle. The engine roared as it completed its atmospheric descent, following the Terran glide slope. The Arxur vessel slammed onto the open deck, and our personnel eyed it warily.

There’s a human sniper watching them from the mast. I wonder if the grays noticed…better hope my friends can react quicker than those demons can snap me in half.

Paralyzing terror coursed through my bloodstream, as dozens of Arxur lumbered out into the open. They lugged some supply crates onto the deck, and waved for the humans to collect them. Terran personnel scurried over to sort through the offerings. I could see in the primates’ eyes that they were concerned about opening up a cattle ‘gift.’

One Arxur was directing the others, with the cracked skin around its eyes suggesting its age. Its nostrils flared with obvious hunger, entranced by the whiff of Venlil in the breeze. Ghastly reptilian eyes snapped my way, and yellowed teeth flared in a ferocious snarl. Why had Marcel’s benign canines ever frightened me?

The enemy commander began ambling toward us. It leaned forward as it walked, poised to drop into a primal lunge in a heartbeat. Its pupils were darker than the frigid side of Venlil Prime, and its drab scales glistened like obsidian. I could see the saliva coagulating around its lips.

“It’s okay, Slanek. I’m right here,” Marcel growled.

My heart hammered so furiously that I swayed on my feet; the human caught me with steady hands. All thoughts were shutting down, like a hard reset to the noggin. Every conscious impulse screamed to propel myself into the ocean, but my brain signals weren’t registering.

I sank my claws into the human’s forearm, whimpering like wounded prey. Tears flowed down my face, dripping onto his pale skin. Marcel massaged my scruff, and tried to stop me from shaking uncontrollably. His gentle touch wasn’t enough to counter an Arxur, standing right across from me.

How could we have ever considered such an abomination sapient? It was the spitting image of death itself. Nothing motivated it, other than its appetite and its cruelty.

“Greetings. I’m going to assume you’re in charge, since you have a Venlil…attached.” The Arxur’s warm breath hit me on the cheek, as it spoke in a reverberating roar. “My name is Chief Hunter Isif. We understand this was the United Nations headquarters, so I decided to accompany this landing party.”

Marcel cleared his throat. “What can I do for you?”

A faint sliver of awareness crept back in. I didn’t understand why my human wouldn’t point this monster toward the actual officers…and far away from us. I wanted to study the vegetarian’s expression, but I couldn’t turn my eyes away from the Arxur. It hadn’t stopped staring at me from the moment it approached.

“Requesting permission to set up emergency housing. I can have structures and basic amenities organized in a day,” Isif barked.

“I don’t think that’ll be an issue,” the red-haired human said. “If you’re aiding search-and-rescue, would you come with me to a neighborhood called Midwood? The people in those bunkers are a UN priority.”

“Gladly. I’ll pick several of my finest to accompany you.”

“Oh, and tell your soldiers not to desecrate any human bodies.”

“Cut it out. We don’t eat each other, whatever the Federation told you. So why would any of us want to eat humans?”

The chief hunter’s eyes lingered on me, the actualization of every nightmare I ever had. My spine pressed back against Marcel’s chest, using his muscular form for support. Every muscle in my body felt weak as jelly, and my nerves were overstimulated beyond salvaging. I wanted to crawl under a rock, and never show my face again.

The Arxur sighed, slinking off with a swish of its tail. It conversed with some Terran personnel for a moment, then issued emphatic orders. Several grays filed into a human “helicopter”, a strange aircraft that had twin blades on its roof. The racket stung my ears, as the propeller revved to life.

“Okay. I don’t expect you to come with me, Slanek.” Marcel released a forceful exhale, and set me back on my paws. “But getting to my family can’t wait…I have to know.”

“So you’re hitching a ride with the child-eating predators?! What will Nulia think if she is alive?” I spat. “You just said you have nightmares about those things devouring her.”

“Using the Arxur will get me there quickest. I’m sorry. There’s no line I won’t cross…I have nothing to live for without them.”

“What about me? I care about you. After what we’ve been through together—”

“Don’t make this about you, buddy. I get why Sovlin losing his family broke him now. If they’re dead, so am I.”

“Marcel, p-please—”

“Go home, Slanek. I hope you succeed in all your future aspirations. Thank you for giving a predator like me a chance.”

The red-haired human shouldered his rifle and duffel bag, and limped over to the waiting helicopter. Those hazel eyes never so much as glanced back; his slender fingers were curled into a fist. Recollections of my predator, starving and beaten, darted through my mind. I could see those same hands pressed up against the glass, as he reached out with the last of his strength.

Marcel tried to protect me in his final moments too, through unimaginable pain. I can’t let him throw his life away.

I remembered how helpless I felt, watching the vegetarian held at gunpoint. The pain in his eyes had been like glass shards in my heart. The thought of never speaking to him again, and learning that the Arxur chopped him up into little pieces…it filled me with the same despair.

How did my Terran friend expect me to abandon him to a senseless fate? Riding along on this suicide misadventure was out of the question though. Marcel wasn’t engaged in proper thinking right now; he needed someone to drill some sense into him. Humans were significantly weaker than the Arxur, so he’d be helpless when they ambushed him.

“Damn you!” I scampered after the hobbling human, who was only a few paces from the chopper. “I nursed you back from death’s door, went with you to a Gojid warzone, and stayed here when we all thought your Earth was going to be glassed to the core!”

Marcel clambered up into the chopper. “You’ve done enough. Go away, Slanek; get lost.”

“And go home, like none of this happened? I’m telling you, as your friend, not to do this. I need you safe and alive, and I don’t care if that’s ‘making this about me.’”

I bounded the last several steps, and hurled myself at the human’s leg in desperation. My hindlegs scrabbled for traction on the floor; I struggled with all my might to pull the bulky predator off the helicopter. Marcel panted, and shook me off with a grunt. The Arxur passengers watched with amusement.

The human set his supplies on an empty seat, adjacent to the cockpit. Chief Hunter Isif was ordering the Terran pilot he’d borrowed to take off. I had to get my friend out of here now.

With panicked desperation, I yanked at his injured arm. Marcel could forgive me for the pain that caused later. It was the only way to mitigate his superior strength, and save him from his own recklessness.

“Shit!” he cursed. “Get the fuck off of me.”

The vegetarian’s eyes dilated with frustration, and his cheeks turned that flushed shade of red that unnerved me. His teeth bared with obvious hostility; that was no human smile causing his jaw to tremble. I wasn’t about to be scared away by growling, even if it made my throat go dry. He was never going to hurt me.

Marcel pried my claws off of him with predatory strength; his typical gentleness was gone. I mewled in protest, but the human clenched his fingers into my scruff. He carried me toward the exit in cold silence, and seemed ready to toss me outside. My legs flailed about in desperation, but the struggling didn’t have much effect.

The helicopter rose the first few feet off the ground. Chief Hunter Isif retreated from the cockpit, and darted between Marcel and the exit. The Arxur commander slid the door shut, sealing off the escape route for both of us. Its eyes widened in confusion, as it noticed me dangling like a pup from the human’s hands.

“Take a seat. There’s room for you and the animal,” it snarled. “Per the map overlay, this should be a short ride.”

The aircraft was ascending rapidly, now above the mast in altitude. My heart sank in my chest, compounded by sheer panic. Jumping from this height would be suicide, though it might be better than being turned into cattle. Not only had I failed to get Marcel away from these monsters, but I had ended up escapeless with him.

The red-haired human adjusted his grip, bringing me into the normal carrying position. I burrowed my head against his shirt, and he patted me with a sigh. Isif watched with keen interest, as the Terran settled in to his chosen seat. The vegetarian placed my shaking body on his lap, and turned my chin toward the window with a delicate push.

I was certain the other Arxur were gaping at us, and salivating at the flesh on my skeleton. My hope was that my presence would stop the grays from eating Marcel; Venlil were a juicier target, after all. That didn’t lessen the dread in my heart. There was nothing worse than being trapped, hundreds of feet above the ground, with feral carnivores.

⋯ ✧ ⋯ ✧ ⋯

Chapter 73
Memory transcription subject:

Slanek,
Venlil Space Corps

Date [standardized human time]:
November 27, 2136

The shuttle was crammed full of predators, so much so, that several humans were standing throughout the bumpy ride. I was lucky that I could curl up in Marcel's lap; the red-haired vegetarian had a steely glint in his eyes. I hadn't seen this much apprehension in him, not even during the Gojid cradle's chaos. Something about the Tilfish seemed to inspire fear in Terrans, without an apparent reason.

The superocean was visible on the horizon, as we descended on the sole continent of planet Sillis. The Terran pilots appeared to be half-expecting the natives to shoot our transport down. The United Nations had officially accepted the Tilfish surrender, today; this was the start of bringing their territory under human control. It was possible that we'd see combat, but on paper, our interactions should be restricted to civilian policing.

Marcel grew restless after Earth's raid, especially once he heard that my redeployment was requested. There was no hesitation from me, to put in formal consent papers to the Venlil government. Oddly enough, I'd begun to feel comfortable around the rowdy predators; living in close quarters with grown beasts was the new normal. The anti-instinct training made me feel empowered for the first time in my life, and I wanted to prove that I was a changed man.

It is awesome that my buddy has recovered, and decided to come with me. After what the Krakotl did, retiring on the homefront is out of the question.

I cleared my throat. "What do you think about races like the Tilfish being predators, Marc? We haven't really talked about it."

"It makes a lot more sense than everyone but us and the grays being obligate herbivores," Marcel growled. "But, they're not predators, Slanek. And it doesn't change the fact that they participated in the murder of a billion people."

I straightened my blinders with a paw. "Maybe it's possible to reverse the cure though. Humans already started studying the Gojid genome."

When Cilany's broadcast arrived back on Earth, it was plastered across every news feed. Terran discussion panels had mixed opinions on alien victimhood, but the "cure" was something all of them lambasted. The Kolshians found themselves vying for public enemy number one. Even the more xenophobic humans considered allying with any converted race that would take the fight to Aafa.

Whatever ties the Venlil still had to the Federation, the conspiracy reframed our stance. How could the Federation mastermind such a heinous crime, as altering species' identity, for centuries? None of their atrocities had ever been defensible, in my eyes, but I had believed their intentions were good. Every act of bigotry was an attempt to protect their citizens from a malevolent enemy.

Marcel inspected my far-away expression. "Do you feel sorry for the cured races?"

"I don't know. There's some things about humans that bother me, but I tried to accept you," I said. "What right do I have to impose my evolution on you? To erase your history and beliefs? These species lost everything that makes them...well, themselves."

"You're right. It's a cultural genocide that was thoroughly executed, without anyone's knowledge or consent. I shudder to think what would've happened to humanity, if they found us before the Arxur."

I couldn't imagine the predators, reduced to terrified prey; stripped of the resilience and aggression that defined them. It wasn't clear to me if violent instincts could be written out of the human genome, or how the Kolshians might've worked around the binocular eyes. Would cultural indoctrination stick to such a strong-willed species?

The Terran transport touched down on a landing pad, following Tilfish signals. I was relieved that we'd set this spacecraft on the ground, rather than jumping out of it. The UN troops unloaded, grimacing as wind gusts buffeted their faces. Sillis was known for its stormy, tumultuous weather, which was fueled by the panthalassa.

A lone Tilfish waited for us, scuttling back and forth with anxiety. "H-hello, humans. I brought...gifts."

The insectoid gestured with one of her six legs to fruit baskets, which included local jams and preserves. She cowed her glistening head, as several Terrans trained guns on her. Her antennae quivered, anticipating her swift demise. The poor thing was surrounded by predators; forward-facing eyes were angled at her in all directions.

Why did her species send her here alone? This is cruel.

"Thanks for the gifts. Who are you?" I asked.

Tears bordered her smooth eyes. "I'm...G-General Birla. Ambassador D-Dwirl made me come. I am the only one...who, uh, v-voted against...Earth attack..."

The UN soldiers relaxed, but shared a few rattled glances of their own. Several were huddling near the shuttle, distancing themselves from Birla. The faint hairs on Marcel's arm stood upright, and he ruffled my ears for comfort. I coaxed him forward, bringing us across from the Tilfish.

"Slanek, what are you doing?" the human hissed.

My ears pinned back. "Face your fears, right? That's what I did with you. This is no different."

General Birla bent lower to the ground, unable to look the human in the eye. A ripple passed through Marcel's throat, before he narrowed his pupils. The human extended a trembling hand, keeping his palm flat. The Tilfish must've been briefed on Terran mannerisms, because she placed a delicate leg atop his fingers.

"Well, at least someone on this rock has a conscience," the vegetarian wheezed, jerking his arm back. "Where can we set up shop? With any luck, the ground occupation will get rolled back soon."

Birla flicked her antennae in the city's direction. "F-follow me. Please. The—there's a few things you should know."

Marcel tucked his hands behind his back, trying to look formal as the squad leader. The medals on his chest were recent adornments. The new Secretary-General issued them to anyone wounded in defense of Earth or the cradle. I couldn't think of anyone who deserved a commendation more than my friend.

"Go on, he's listening," I chimed in. "Is there something to be concerned about, General?"

Birla clicked her mandibles. "We're...having t-trouble with unrest and dissidents. M-mass protests...many people don't want a human invasion."

Marcel raised his eyebrows. "That doesn't surprise me at all. How bad is it?"

"The exterminators pulled t-together some rogue generals. They're offering a bounty for every human killed. We'd deal with it, but the surrendering members complied with your disarmament demands."

"And the anti-human factions didn't hand over their weapons, leaving your government with no way to stop them."

"Exactly. L-look, not every p-protestor is violent...there's demonstrations everywhere, like I said. I don't know if you allow such things, b-but..."

"Last I checked, the UN affirms the right to free speech. But we may impose martial law, until things settle down."

The Tilfish general shuddered with relief, before climbing onto a monorail train. The insectoid retreated to the furthest corner as the Terrans piled in, and automated doors sealed us in the tight space. Marcel ensured that all equipment was brought aboard, before leaning against a wall. I nuzzled his elbow, desperate for attention.

The human smiled, as he tickled my chin. "You are still adorable, Slanek. You could get away with anything."

"Anything?" I repeated, with a devious ear flick. "What if I told the Tilfish that you want to give her a belly rub?"

"No! You little shit...you wouldn't."

I didn't respond, turning to the window with a contented stare. Marcel withdrew his hand, crossing his arms with an irritated huff. The vegetarian noted the mirth in my eyes, as the supersonic train hurtled along. But the playfulness seeped out of my demeanor, once I caught glimpses of the chaos.

Judging by the corpses in the streets, stampeding began prior to our arrival. The human soldiers peered out the windows, though the carnage was an unfocused blur. Bringing a predator military to a homeworld inspired panic, especially for the stated purpose of an occupation. The grisly sight reminded me of the cradle, when we rescued Nulia.

Whatever the Tilfish once were, this is not hunter behavior. The public sure isn't lumping themselves in with humans.

General Birla twisted her antennae, scrutinizing the predators' responses. I half-expected Marcel to stop the train, and rush off to help the victims. Instead, the red-haired human pursed his lips with discomfort. Our top priority was subduing the populace, and making the area safe for Terran travel.

The train glided to its stopping point, a terminal which emptied into a city square. The humans continued to gawk at the scenery, while clutching their guns tighter. Tilfish protestors were packed into the square; the ones that hadn't fled the settlement came out as a welcoming party. Insect bodies spanned as far as the eye could see.

"Good grief. We've got to get them to disperse," Marcel muttered. "A gathering of this size, in our faces..."

The vegetarian conferred with several comrades, before the grunts began assembling equipment. I hoped there was non-lethal weaponry in their cache. These were civilians exercising sapient rights Earth validated. It would disappoint me if humanity began their reign by squashing all expression.

General Birla clicked her mandibles. "You n-need a way through the crowd? We s-saved armored vehicles for you. Please...n-no massacre."

"Will humans even fit in your trucks?" Marcel asked, with raised eyebrows. "I can't imagine your sitting arrangements are meant for us. These train seats look like step-stools with six tiny holes inserted."

"We replaced t-the upholstery with biped-designed seats. Like we use with Venlil or Kolshian guests."

The Terran soldiers lugged some sort of speaker out of the train. The predators clambered atop a vehicle's hood, and secured the acoustic device to the roof. Marcel hopped into the flatbed, which I took as my cue to follow. These trucks were not self-driving like the ones on Earth; another human moved behind the wheel.

Tilfish protestors jeered at the sight of us. Several individuals sported homemade exterminator gear; lighters and matches were among "weapons" I saw. My human shouted for every friendly to stay behind the truck, before bringing a microphone to his mouth.

"Please return to your homes," Marcel barked. "Martial law is in effect until further notice. Public gatherings are not permitted until the United Nations has secured the area. Locally-sanctioned curfews will be enforced."

"Die, predator scum!" a voice shrieked.

More followed in quick succession. "We're not like you, no matter what any Kolshian says!"

"I will not be your cattle."

"Human filth don't belong on Sillis. BURN!"

Chants of 'Burn' swept across the gathering, and the agitated protestors closed on our position. This was no longer about sapient rights; the situation changed the second they threatened my friends. Nobody was going to torch my human alive. The thought of him suffering again twisted my heart.

The blinders were helpful in narrowing the scope of the incident. I focused on compartmentalizing my emotions, listing the facts to myself. We were the ones with guns, backed by a predator army. Even if the situation worsened, all I needed to do was pick off a single target.

You can do this, Slanek. Your fear does not control your actions. You want to protect Marc.

I raised my gun with a steady grip, but Marcel's eyes widened in alarm. He pushed the barrel down with a palm, shaking his head. My ears pinned back, not sure why the human stopped me from defending myself. Wasn't that what they wanted me to do?

"Killing should be a last resort," the vegetarian hissed. "Always. Life is a precious thing. Non-lethal options are going to be exhausted first."

Marcel fiddled with the settings on his speaker. There was nothing audible to my sensitive ears, but waves of Tilfish halted in their tracks. The insects began clutching audio sensors, and some vomited. The device must be concentrating amplified sound in a narrow beam; none of the humans behind the truck were affected.

There was the verdict: Terrans weaponized everything. Marcel, as gentle as he was, had planned for the eventuality of disorder from the beginning. I imagined he'd also brought other tools in case the sonic attack didn't work. The predators always had a backup plan or a contingency, since I'd worked with them.

UN soldiers began firing grenades into the crowd, which drew a cacophony of screams. But rather than maiming the civilians, it dispersed a milky gas into the air. I wondered if it was a sleeping vapor, at first. The effects kicked in almost immediately, leaving Tilfish crying and coughing. Blinded, several staggered out of the gas cloud in a loopy panic.

I winced with sympathy at the collapsed bodies, recognizing that they were in severe pain. Perhaps the unruly Tilfish would take this as proof of human cruelty, but I saw it for what it was. It was an attempt to incapacitate a hostile group, without any desire to kill civilians. These measures flourished on Earth, due to the violence of Terran stampedes.

Marcel cleared his throat. "Please disperse. We do not wish to arrest or harm anyone. A designated time will be set to air grievances in a civilized manner."

The vegetarian spoke in an impassive voice, like this was an ordinary decree. Some Tilfish heeded his warning this time, trying to escape the jam-packed square. The agonizing weapons must've made them rethink swarming the predator's locale.

The humans took the crowd's disorientation as a chance to push forward. Our vehicles rolled ahead, with a line of soldiers leading the way. UN guards in stampede gear began grabbing a few Tilfish, and wrangled them into custody. Unwilling insects were hauled away from their friends, shrieking and writhing.

Marcel repeated his warning about the planet being under Terran control. The sight of advancing predators, bulked up from head-to-toe, was enough to spark flight responses in all but the boldest few. With the civilians flushed out of our immediate vicinity, we could find a campsite.

"You are efficient," General Birla decided. "Much more organized than the grays. And you took p-prisoners..."

Humor flickered in my human's eyes. "We're not going to execute people off the streets, if that's what you're implying. Our job is to stabilize the region, and integrate Sillis as a UN vassal."

"What does our planet look like under your rule? I w-worry about being beholden to predators. Especially if...we are what they say. We might, uh, regress."

"Annexation comes with certain rights and privileges, unlike total war. We're not forcing anyone to modify their lifestyle or beliefs."

For all the baseless fears, of human predation being contagious, not a single Venlil in the exchange program developed an appetite for murder. What I had been forced to do was broaden my horizons. Earth was untamed and dangerous; the perilous environment helped me modify my beliefs.

The idea of controlling my instincts, and tolerating some risk, became palatable. I achieved feats I didn't know were possible, for someone of a meek disposition. Humans challenged my preconceptions at every turn. Their friendship and their empathy, how my bond with Marcel was close as family...that impacted me more than binocular eyes ever could.

"Getting paired with Marcel is the best thing that ever happened to me," I said. "He is patient and kind. You can trust him."

The human bared his teeth. "Thanks, buddy. We make a good team."

Our exchange hadn't convinced the Tilfish general, but I saw hope in her story. A single official had the conviction to stand up for the predators; to believe that they deserved to live. Sillis had been relinquished without a drop of bloodshed so far. Even if it was a disproportionate balance, some civilians could come around.

Marcel outlined plans for humanity to cement a foothold in the city, and gather a tally of its populace. The masses were in shock from Cilany's interview; they needed help deriving meaning. We'd spend a few days getting settled, before we reclaimed rogue areas. Havens for anti-human extermination officers and military leaders were the real issue.

Clearing those territories might be where the Terrans summoned their lethal arsenal. The United Nations would have this newly-conquered world brought to heel, one way or another.

⋯ ✧ ⋯ ✧ ⋯

Capítulo 76
Memoria del sujeto de transcripción:

Capitán Sovlin,
Comando de la Flota de las Naciones Unidas

Fecha [tiempo humano estandarizado]:
28 de noviembre de 2136

La flota humana mantuvo sus posiciones, mientras el mundo natal de los Mazic se encontraba en una situación precaria. Nuestra llamada seguía transmitiéndose, aunque el enemigo no la había respondido. Un transporte de evacuación salió de la atmósfera, llevando a civiles a un lugar seguro. Los Kolshians impactaron la nave con plasma, y apuntaron con precisión para dejarla fuera de servicio. Parecía que no intentaban destruirla, después de todo.

Las fosas nasales del Capitán Monahan se ensancharon con agitación. "Coalición de la Federación, si vuelven a disparar a objetivos civiles, nuestro alto al fuego terminará. No toleraremos tales acciones."

Un Kolshian violeta apareció en una pantalla holográfica. "¿No van a sacrificar a los Mazic por la victoria y la gloria? ¿En realidad son lo suficientemente inteligentes como para no mostrar su lado despiadado?"

"Me pregunto quiénes son los despiadados, cuando son ustedes los que amenazan a una población civil. No me importa la victoria; estamos aquí para salvar vidas. Eso es lo que representan los humanos."

El comandante enemigo caminó de un lado a otro, sin inmutarse por la imagen de un depredador. Su tripulación era un grupo homogéneo de Kolshians, en lugar de incluir extraterrestres. La superficie esmeralda de Khoa era visible en su ventana, junto con tres objetivos bloqueados en la pantalla de sensores. Si no supiera más, pensaría que el oficial de la Commonwealth no sabía qué hacer.

Agitó un tentáculo. "Maldición. Nunca quisimos matarlos; queríamos matarlos a ustedes. Esta pelea no debería haber sucedido así."

"Dime algo que no haya escuchado antes," refunfuñó Samantha a mi lado.

Tyler la miró con furia. "¡Silencio!"

Afortunadamente, el comentario de mi guardia no fue captado en la llamada; una palabra equivocada podría terminar en una catástrofe para los civiles. Me alivió escuchar que los Kolshians no querían iniciar el bombardeo. Al menos había algo de moralidad entre sus filas, por muy baja que fuera la barra. La capitana Terran tomó la declaración incendiaria con calma y frunció los labios.

"Bueno, ¿por qué no nos enfrentan entonces? ¿Qué es lo que quieren?" exigió Monahan.

Los ojos del Kolshian se abultaron. "Queremos que dejen de ganar poder, depredadores. Nikonus tiene razón; no muestran moderación en sus guerras. Su agresión es la de los Krakotl, multiplicada por cien."

"¿Y su solución a esta percepción es la agresión desmedida de su parte? Les garantizo que si bombardean Khoa, le darán a más especies razones para abandonar la Federación. No pueden deshacer millones de muertes. Esa sangre estará en su conciencia para siempre."

"Entonces retrocedan. No lo harán; son demasiado orgullosos."

"No puedo hacer eso. Especialmente dada su historia de cambiar especies, irreversiblemente."

"Entonces, ¿qué ciudad debería bombardear primero, depredador? Escuché que Tlinio tiene una alta capacidad industrial... lástima que también es un bullicioso centro civil."

La capitana depredadora tenía las manos detrás de la espalda, pero podía ver sus uñas clavándose en la palma. Esa indignación era algo que compartía, al escuchar amenazas tan frías contra el planeta. Me recordó a la indiferencia de los Arxur por los civiles; los Kolshians podrían haber estudiado a los cazadores demasiado. Negociar con vidas era deshonroso.

Monahan mostró los dientes y arqueó las cejas. "Esa es su prerrogativa. Pero cuando la humanidad llegue a Aafa, y lo haremos, arrasaremos una ciudad Kolshian por cada bomba que arrojen aquí. Sangre por sangre. ¿Deberíamos comenzar con la Escuela de la Flora, o tienen un sustituto en mente?"

"Tú—"

"Cállate. Si se rinden ahora, trataremos a su gente bajo nuestras reglas de guerra; como prisioneros con un trato justo. Confíen en mí, debido a esas guerras desmedidas que vieron, quieren que apliquemos las Convenciones de Ginebra. Será un mal día para ustedes si decidimos que ya no son aplicables."

Recordé la explicación de mi abogado, sobre la prohibición de tortura de la ONU. Tenía curiosidad por saber qué otros crímenes y dispositivos los terrícolas habían desterrado en esos acuerdos. Era una apuesta segura que los artilugios que los humanos consideraban demasiado depravados para usar, estaban más allá de nuestros peores sueños. Todos los depredadores son propensos a la crueldad incomprensible; por eso había podido torturar a Marcel con tanta saña.

Los humanos son capaces de todo lo que han hecho los Arxur. Eligen no hacerlo... pero nadie quiere verlos descontrolarse por completo.

El miedo brilló en los ojos dorados del comandante Kolshian. La intensidad en la mirada hambrienta de Monahan le dio un peso adicional a su amenaza; era como mirar al rostro de la muerte. Ese ceño fruncido implacable era una afirmación de dominio, ya fuera consciente o no. Me resultó difícil encogerme de hombros ante su animosidad, aunque no estaba dirigida a mí.

"Prefiero morir antes que ver a cualquiera de mis hombres rendirse ante ustedes. En cuanto a Aafa, no mostrarían su crueldad mientras se hacen pasar por presas," siseó el Kolshian.

Monahan se encogió de hombros. "Estás confundido. O somos depredadores agresivos que no pueden controlarse, o mostramos moderación. Elige uno."

"Yo... ¡estás torciendo mis palabras! Bicho raro alienígena."

"No tengo tiempo para insultos mezquinos. ¿Cuál es una forma aceptable de sacarte muy, muy lejos de este sistema? Eso es lo que todos queremos."

El oficial de la Commonwealth mostró una expresión afligida. El odio brillaba en sus ojos, y echó un vistazo a su tripulación en el puente. Ningún capitán quiere ver morir a sus subordinados. Siempre me sentí responsable cuando mis planes salían mal y había bajas; las decisiones recaían en el comandante.

El Kolshian vio en los rostros de los subordinados cuánto anhelaban escapar de los depredadores. La perspectiva de ser cazados por humanos los aterrorizaba; los terrícolas eran demasiado metódicos para ser superados. Los Arxur podían ser descuidados debido a sus aspiraciones de comida, pero los primates trataban la guerra como una ecuación matemática. Buscaban la solución más simple para dejar al enemigo muerto.

"Dejen que 1500 de nuestras naves se vayan, y no intenten perseguirlas. Unos cientos de nosotros nos quedaremos atrás," decidió el líder enemigo. "Si nos escanean siquiera, ordenaré que Khoa sea bombardeada con el resto."

Monahan se enderezó. "Una decisión inteligente. No quieren perder tantas naves, con todas las almas a bordo. La ONU les permitirá huir; eso es aceptable para mis parámetros."

Onso escudriñó la ventana, mientras la actividad de las naves aumentaba alrededor del planeta. La flota Terran abrió vías para las salidas enemigas y no hizo esfuerzos por enfrentarlas. Cuantos más hostiles sacáramos del área, menores serían las bajas máximas. Esto era un paso en la dirección correcta, en mi opinión.

El Yotul negó con la cabeza. "¿Debería prepararme para la persecución? No podemos simplemente dejar que esos bastardos se vayan."

"Esperaré las órdenes del capitán, pero imagino que cumpliremos nuestra palabra. Establece un buen precedente, poder negociar," respondió Tyler.

Carlos miró a Sam. "Sé lo que estás pensando, pero sería bueno tener opciones sobre la mesa. Tal vez incluso comiencen a permitirnos rendirnos, dándonos derechos sapientes."

La humana resopló. "Sigue soñando. Nos prefieren muertos."

"A veces, creo que la Federación también nos prefiere muertos. Pero la verdad es que no les importamos en absoluto," escupió Onso. "¿Sabían que ofrecieron destruir nuestros ferrocarriles y barcos de vapor?"

Mis ojos se estrecharon ante la distorsión de los eventos por parte del elevado. La Federación ya no era mi facción favorita, pero eliminar tecnología obsoleta era útil. No entendía por qué los humanos le daban miradas de simpatía. El disgusto cruzó la expresión de Tyler, y Carlos también arrugó la nariz.

Masticé mis garras. "Bueno, ya no los necesitas. Estás atrapado en el pasado, Onso. No hay razón para mantener reliquias."

Onso frunció el labio. "¡Eso es lo que dijeron! Lo llamaron una celebración, mientras demolían nuestros astilleros. Tal vez todavía nos gustan las cosas que construimos."

"Pero la tecnología de la Federación es mejor. ¿Esto es sobre orgullo?"

"El orgullo no es buscar tu propia identidad. ¡Al diablo contigo!"

Carlos me golpeó el cuello. "Borrar la cultura y las creencias de alguien es una forma de genocidio. Pensaría que tú, de todas las personas, entenderías eso, Sovlin."

Tyler me lanzó una mirada furiosa antes de irse a consolar a Onso. La mención de mi nombre fue suficiente para hacer hervir su sangre; la brecha entre nosotros no se había cerrado. Mi maldad no era su culpa, y nunca había sido mi intención interrumpir su trabajo. Cuando se resolviera la crisis actual, le debía una disculpa al humano alto.

Los Kolshians que huían habían puesto cierta distancia entre ellos y Khoa, mientras corrían para escapar del alcance de los disruptores FTL. Me imaginé que estaban mirando por encima del hombro en busca de depredadores persiguiéndolos. Ninguno de ellos aflojó el acelerador, ya que ser el rezagado de la manada era una sentencia de muerte. Pero los humanos resistieron la tentación de perseguir; rara vez sucumbían a los deseos de cazador.

Los Terrícolas pueden comportarse como personas normales, a pesar de sus déficits. Nunca deja de impresionarme.

"Es hermoso, ¿no es así?" La capitana Monahan le dio la espalda a la cámara, mirando las estrellas. "Nunca tuvimos que pelear. Podríamos trabajar para hacer algo mejor."

"Deja de mentir. Contando colonias, 34 mundos han sido arrasados desde que los conocimos. Y han estado aquí por cuatro meses," murmuró el Kolshian.

"Nosotros no comenzamos, ni siquiera bombardeamos, ninguno de esos. No es nuestra culpa que todos sigan atacándonos y abandonen sus defensas."

"Están confabulados con los Arxur... incluso están tirando de los hilos. No los atraerían si no fueran podridos hasta el núcleo. Los humanos disfrutan matar, a pesar de toda su empatía."

"Disfruto deteniendo a las malas personas de lastimar a otros. Nadie más tiene que morir hoy. Ciertamente no rehenes inocentes, porque nos odian. Por nuestro honor, los dejaremos ir a todos ilesos."

El Kolshian se movió incómodo; estaba claro que desconfiaba de la propuesta humana. Varias de las naves que dejó atrás estaban huyendo, sin esperar órdenes. Los capitanes asustadizos no iban a darles a los depredadores tiempo para cambiar de opinión. Me dejó un sabor amargo en la boca ver al enemigo escapando.

"¿Por su honor?" El Kolshian se agitó exasperado. "¿Qué bien me hace eso? Los depredadores engañan."

Monahan resopló. "También lo hacen las 'presas'... mírate. No te he mentido ni una vez, ni lo ha hecho la raza humana. Por favor, piensa en los Mazic."

"Yo... no soy un asesino. No quiero matar niños... herbívoros. Mierda, su truco está funcionando. Nos iremos."

La transmisión de video se apagó antes de que la humana pudiera responder. Las naves Kolshians se deslizaron lejos de la vulnerable superficie de Khoa, manteniendo su formación. La flota Terran honró el pacto de no agresión, en lugar de enfrentar al enemigo. Los depredadores estaban aquí para salvar a sus aliados, ante todo.

La tripulación humana ofreció un aplauso entusiasta al Capitán Monahan, lo que tomó por sorpresa a los extraterrestres. Me había acostumbrado al nivel de ruido de los depredadores, después de vivir entre ellos durante meses. Traer a un Terrícola cerca era una forma rápida de desmantelar la paz y la tranquilidad.

El pobre Fissan en comunicaciones se agitó, y los observadores Venlil se taparon los sensibles oídos. Onso se deleitó con el alboroto, sin embargo, con sus sensibilidades primitivas. El Yotul comenzó a aullar y saltar, como un animal. Monahan permitió la cacofonía por un momento, antes de gritar órdenes para que se callaran. El silencio invadió el puente en un instante.

La capitana Terran suspiró. "No nos felicitemos todavía. Este fue un buen día para nosotros, pero les prometo que los Mazic no lo recordarán con tanto cariño. Comunicaciones, contacten a Khoa."

El mamífero beige en la pantalla respondió de inmediato. Sus ojos estaban frenéticos, como si se hubiera caído para responder. Al inspeccionar más de cerca, reconocí al macho mayor como el Presidente Cupo. El líder Mazic parecía alarmado de estar a merced de la flota depredadora. Sus defensas estaban al descubierto, y el pobre tipo estaba nervioso por el asalto también.

"Saludos," dijo Monahan cortésmente. "¿Necesitan alguna ayuda? Estamos felices de ayudar con la búsqueda y rescate. Hay un transportador civil inmovilizado en órbita, para empezar."

Cupo abrió su trompa. "N-no, gracias. Podemos manejarlo. ¿Qué pago puedo ofrecerles, humanos? Les daremos lo que quieran."

"¿Pago? No queremos nada de ustedes. La humanidad vino en su ayuda porque somos aliados. Ahora son parte de nuestra 'manada', como imagino que lo dirían."

El Mazic guardó silencio por un largo tiempo. Algo parecido al arrepentimiento brilló en su mirada, aunque desapareció un segundo después. El líder se compuso y volvió a la cámara. Parecía aislado, en un búnker vasto con solo un asistente.

"Nunca confié en la humanidad. No estaba dispuesto a arriesgar a mi gente para ayudar a la Tierra," dijo Cupo. "Incluso con la revelación de Cilany, solo comprometí recursos a su equipo porque vi que la Federación era un barco que se hundía. Ahora, ustedes nos protegieron, y lo siento. Por favor, déjennos pagar su ayuda."

La capitana Terran se rió. "Todo está perdonado, Presidente Cupo. Sus elecciones fueron relativamente suaves, comparadas con los maníacos genocidas de la Federación."

"Oh humano, estuve al lado de esas personas durante años. Era maravilloso, todos los herbívoros trabajando juntos, en perfecta armonía. ¿Cómo es que nadie vio la verdad? Yo debería haberlo hecho."

"No se culpe. Todos vemos lo que queremos ver. Al igual que la gente lee maldad en nosotros y selecciona nuestros peores momentos. Porque eso es lo que están buscando."

"Han tenido que arrastrarse y rogar por cada amigo que tienen, humano, pero ya no más. El Presidium Mazic nunca olvidará su heroísmo. Apartaré a mis mejores científicos para apoyar sus esfuerzos de colonización, y pueden elegir entre nuestros mundos abandonados. A menos que les importe estar tan cerca de nosotros."

"Ni un poco. A las Naciones Unidas les encantaría cooperar en el futuro."

Mis orejas se alejaron del diálogo, y me alejé de la estación de sensores. Pasos pronunciados me siguieron de inmediato, y una sombra cayó sobre mi forma. Sin mirar, sabía que era Tyler acechándome; me estaba siguiendo con intenciones depredadoras. El miedo pulsó a través de mi caja torácica, y mis espinas se erizaron hasta el punto de la incomodidad.

Tragando saliva, me dirigí al comedor y me di la vuelta. La mandíbula cincelada del oficial de sensores estaba rígida, sugiriendo que el humano quería morderme. Sus dientes no eran adecuados para eso, pero el subconsciente lo delataba. Esos ojos azules brillaban como hielo, quemando mis áreas vulnerables.

Aclaré mi garganta. "Señor, lamento mi comportamiento inicial. Entré en pánico cuando mencionó a Slanek, y no quería interrumpir—"

Un puño impactó en mi hocico, antes de que pudiera reaccionar. El golpe de Tyler tenía un poder fenomenal, ya que sus huesos calcificados conectaron con mi piel. Me llevé la mano a las fosas nasales sangrantes, y el humano enlazó un codo alrededor de mi cuello. Su rodilla se alzó hacia mi estómago, sacándome el aire.

Me doblé, pero el agarre del depredador me impidió colapsar. El dolor abrumó mis sentidos, y mi mente consciente lo disfrutó. Sin embargo, el control se estaba escapando, ya que el pánico instintivo suprimía mis facultades. Usé lo último de mi lucidez para evitar devolver el golpe.

Tyler apretó su agarre en mi cuello, antes de lanzarme contra un armario. Me estrellé contra el tapizado, desplomándome en una bola. El humano avanzó con zancadas sin esfuerzo, y se cernió sobre mí. Mi corazón estaba al borde de estallar, viendo su gruñido malicioso.

"Esto es lo que se siente ser golpeado físicamente, e impotente para contraatacar. ¡Le hiciste eso a Marcel durante una semana!" escupió el oficial Terran.

"Lo... sé..." tosí la sangre que goteaba en mi boca. "Me o-dio... a mí mismo por eso. Solo... no me suicidé... para que los humanos tuvieran justicia."

El depredador me observó arrastrarme por el suelo, antes de extender una mano áspera. Acepté su pata, permitiéndole levantarme. En lugar de continuar la pelea, Tyler me ayudó a sentarme en una silla. Tomó una toalla de papel del fregadero y la presionó contra mi nariz.

El primate retrocedió. "¿Quieres morir?"

"Claro, pero soy un c-cobarde." Las lágrimas brotaron de mis ojos y rodaron en hilos. "Resulta que soy terrible para matarme, y... para elegir a los monstruos que lastimaron a mi familia. No fue Marcel, pero cualquier depredador servía."

"Mierda, hombre. ¿Alguna vez recibiste tratamiento por TEPT? Lo que pasaste fue bastante jodido. Nunca deberías haber estado en una posición de mando para empezar."

"T-tratamiento para qué? Eso no se tradujo."

"...Ya veo. Deberías hablar con un terapeuta; conozco uno bueno. Es lo que Marcel querría."

Tyler decidió que nuestra pelea había terminado y me dejó para curar mis heridas. ¿Realmente Marcel querría que recibiera tratamiento mental? Mis pensamientos volvieron a mi celda en la Tierra, y al humano pelirrojo burlándose de mi incapacidad para sobrellevarlo. Estaba empezando a creer que se dio cuenta de que el desprecio propio era el peor castigo. ¿No quería que viviera con esta miseria hasta la dulce liberación de la muerte?

Pero Tyler lo conoce personalmente. Si dice que Marcel querría ayudarme...

Con el rescate de Khoa, vi que los humanos defendían la preservación de la vida. Tal vez eso se extendía a alguien como yo, a pesar de mi pasado. Me aterraba explorar mi lado depredador; perder mi identidad había sido devastador. ¿Cómo podría alguien lidiar con que toda su vida fuera una mentira?

Había una certeza, una verdad absoluta, en mi universo ahora. Era que los humanos eran los únicos que podían coser esta galaxia de nuevo.

⋯ ✧ ⋯ ✧ ⋯

Chapter 83
Memory transcription subject:

Glim,
Venlil Rescue

Date [standardized human time]:
November 29, 2136

Public transit on Venlil Prime was always behind schedule, and this tram station was no exception. I was stuck waiting for the next ride out. It was wonderful to see so many people walking around, in a bustling environment. There was still life in their eyes, hope that the humans hadn't quenched yet.

Part of me wished I didn't know the truth of the "Gaians." Would they ever have told us their identity at all? Happiness wasn't the worst thing to dupe myself into believing. It killed me to know that another predator species existed, one that was more warlike than the Arxur...

We were all doomed to a life of servitude and torment; no amount of rumination would fix that. Many cattle grew resigned to that reality, after dealing with the Arxur on a daily basis. But the exterminator in me craved a way to turn the tables. Colonies we landed on had infestations that were out of control too; so much that we mixed orbital actions with paws-on-the-ground. Could I accept that our home was beyond cleansing?

My thoughts wandered to Haysi, and whether her well-being was intact after my escape. When I was crawling up into the airduct, her shrill scream had permeated the vicinity. It wasn't clear what the Gaians had done, to elicit such a fear response. Perhaps they dropped their 'mask-wearing herbivore' routine.

Forget Haysi now, I decided. You need to monitor every predator in the area.

My cursory head-count was five humans, though I was rechecking the area every minute. It was a matter of time before a predator singled me out; I was sorry-looking and isolated from the herd. Few other Venlil paid any mind to the Gaians, and no signs of stampede behavior emerged. I hoped this train arrived soon.

There was a breath of sanity in my surroundings, as I noticed a mother with three kids carve a wide berth around a human. The predator was entranced with its holopad, and didn't even look up at the delicacies. I could picture it flashing its teeth as the pups screamed, and using its meaty paws to crush their fragile bones.

"Excuse me, mind if I sit here?" a chirpy voice asked.

A royal-blue Krakotl was eyeing my bench seat, and I flicked my tail in a 'Go ahead' gesture. My eyes never left the nearest human, who was talking animatedly into a device. The avian ruffled her feathers, before following my gaze toward the predator. A strange emotion swirled in her pupils, almost like sorrow.

The bird sighed. "Still afraid of humans, are you? I'm nervous to approach them myself. I was born on Venlil Prime, but I feel like they'd blame me for...you know."

I measured my response. "I've been gone for a long time, and, er, w-woke up in the hospital yesterday. I don't know why the predators are here. Everyone gets mad at me for acting normal toward them."

"Oh dear. That's not good. So you got into an accident before Noah and Sara showed up?"

My eyes widened with alarm, as I recognized the names of my slavemasters. Their concealing masks were etched into my memory. Noah's boasts about the human ability to 'manufacture anything' stuck with me too. Those were not the words of a species that had moral qualms over bargaining with the Arxur.

"C-come again. Those names. Who are Noah and Sara?" I squeaked.

The Krakotl tilted her head. "The two astronauts piloting humanity's first FTL ship. Everyone was hiding in bunkers for hours when they showed up. But they came in peace, my friend. Noah and Sara bent over backwards to prove they were harmless."

"They are not harmless! I know t-this Noah and Sara...and Tarva, personally."

"What?! No, you don't. This isn't a funny joke, man, and I don't appreciate—"

"S-sorry. I'm not messing with you, I swear...please, I need the truth. I just, um...have a head injury? Maybe I'm misremembering."

The avian squinted, scrutinizing me for several seconds. I didn't back away from her direct stare, and tucked my ears back in a pleading gesture. This Krakotl had to understand sincerity, when it was plastered all over my features. None of her explanation made sense, but I had to hear this fabrication for myself.

Unless the names were an uncanny coincidence, Noah and Sara were the first to scout our home as their hunting ground. Could any Venlil actually believe a predator came in peace? My firsthand experience was ripe with displays of aggression; I could still hear the Arxur calling us animals.

My neck brand tingled, as I remembered them pressing a rod to my throat. Their eyes sparkled at my screams, but it was too hot to quiet myself. It felt like they were injecting molten lava into my skin. The restraints stopped me from thrashing, as an Arxur licked the newly-charred skin for fun.

"Please stop lying," I pleaded, in a broken voice. "I heard the television, t-talking about war with the Federation. I know humans conquered us."

The Krakotl squawked with alarm. "The Venlil are the closest allies humanity has! Humans adore you; just look around. That war started because the Federation has been gene-modding dozens of species, without their consent. Anyone who doesn't fit their mold of a model herbivore gets 'cured.'"

"I beg your pardon? That's a total falsification. Humans lie, if that's your source; I would know."

"The Kolshian chief admitted it from the Federation summit, buddy. Also, my species spearheaded an orbital raid on the human homeworld, unprovoked. Killed a billion civilians, and that's why they have so many refugees still here. It makes me ashamed to be a Krakotl."

Of course the Federation tried to exterminate those monsters. Good for them, I thought. But what's with this genetic tampering?

The light-rail train coasted into the station, and an automated voice announced that passengers should begin boarding. The Krakotl hopped off of the bench, leaving me to march after her. There was no telling how much of this story, if any, was true. However, she believed it with all of her heart. That meant the predators might've sold these falsehoods to the Venlil too.

I jostled the avian's wing. "Hey, wait up! How many Venlil...d-do you think they've eaten so far?"

"Zero," she replied, settling into a window seat. "Humans don't eat sapients, and they see you as part of their pack."

"You're really trying to say it's zero? I know it's a non-zero number. Has the whole world gone mad?"

"Yes, I guess it has. That's enough questions. I don't want the humans to think I'm one of those Krakotl...they probably do already."

My gaze turned to the train cabin, as two 'Gaians' boarded together. Silent curses echoed through my mind, at the thought of having to ride with them. There was safety in numbers, since we had enough Venlil to form a herd. Still, I was hoping none of the predators would tag along for our voyage. It made me queasy to picture them ravaging the tram.

One human gazed directly at our seat for a long moment. My heart leapt further into my throat, before I realized that its pupils were on my Krakotl seatmate instead. The shaven beast seemed to be testing the bird, as it arched the hair over its nasty eyes. My avian partner raised a wing slightly, and lowered her head to appease the Gaians.

The Krakotl Alliance attacking the predators' birthplace must have a shred of truth to it. That destructive event explained the ubiquitous invasion of our home; Gaians had been forced to flee their lair. It also meant humans weren't as strong as Noah claimed. There was hope for the Federation to put them down yet.

Attention please. This line is now departing for Tonalu City. Enjoy a safe ride, and please come back soon!

The train doors started to seal, and I relaxed a bit. That was before I caught the blur of motion in my periphery, as a panicked human chased the tram. At first, I assigned menial lateness to the beast's actions. Its brown eyes simmered with determination, and it flailed its arms at the conductor.

"STOP THE TRAIN!" the Gaian roared. "WE NEED TO SEARCH YOU!"

The Krakotl beside me gasped. "Sweet Ina...ah, not supposed to say that anymore. That's Ambassador Noah!"

Excited chatter circulated through the train, and several Venlil flung themselves against the windows to film the incident. You would think it was a superstar celebrity, not an alien hunter. Noah's lean torso made its pose intimidating, and its thin scalp gave it a hardened look. Its forward-facing irises popped against their white backdrop.

I could picture it speaking in a falsetto voice, as it squeezed my paw. That was the vicious face it had been hiding. Governor Tarva plodded up calmly beside it, with a curly-haired human next to her. The female 'Gaian' had thick eyebrows, which accentuated her wildness. Her mane was a total catastrophe, puffing out like windblown grass.

We apologize for this delay. Please remain seated as we speak with the Terran ambassador.

"No!" I screamed. "K-keep going!"

My avian seatmate flexed her talons. "You're crying. What's wrong?"

"I wanna see my family! I CAN'T DO THIS ANYMORE!"

Governor Tarva heard my commotion, and pointed toward the source with her metal tail. Noah waved at the conductor, as the reopened doors granted it entry. It prowled down the aisle, searching with singular intent. I leaned back against the Krakotl in terror, shaking from head to toe. This was like being captured by the Arxur all over again.

My team had descended a canyon, cleaning up native predators there. The region could become an abscess for a fledgling colony otherwise. It was supposed to be a simple job, but none of us realized we weren't alone. The Arxur snuck a ship in under nightfall, and landed practically atop my unit. We all knew it was better to die than to be captured.

I scrambled to the truck to get my firearm, along with every Venlil that didn't freeze. The grays were faster, covering ground with animalistic fervor. A tranquilizer dart embedded in my neck, pricking into my flesh. Sheer terror washed over me, because I knew what the darkness entailed.

"Glim! Tarva heard your voice." The male Gaian worked its way down the aisle, and turned its head from side-to-side. "We're all worried about you. Let us help you."

I glared at Noah's lumbering form. "T-this time, I'll get it right. D-death before c-capture."

I climbed over a number of seats, whacking disgruntled passengers with my tail. Noah spotted my haphazard escape, and chased after me. The human asked for passengers to intervene. Nearby Venlil didn't hesitate to attempt a takedown.

Two of my own people grabbed at me, as I made it to the emergency hatch. My hindlegs kicked one assailant in the teeth, and I shook off the other with a sudden tug. My claws slid under the lever, pulling the panel open. I dove out the window like I was trying to land on my stomach.

The bulky predator took one look at the gap, before settling for the rear exit. My belly flop knocked the wind out of me, but adrenaline pushed me upright. I sprinted with all of my energy, heading in the opposite direction from Noah. Holopads captured my flight in real time.

"GLIM! Our eyes are...arboreal!" the Gaian panted. "Helps...judge...branch distances!"

The predator sounded out of breath, which meant it might give up the pursuit soon. I ignored its words, and hoisted myself up a flight of stairs. The human was quick despite its size, able to track me excellently. Tree-dwellers wouldn't have such a knack for land pursuit, or such wide pupils.

Why is it still trying to lie? All it does is lie!

Noah crested the stairs on my tail. "And the canines...aren't...for meat eating! They're for fighting over mates."

"That's better?" I screamed.

"To you, yes! They've shrunk, from our ancestors...we don't even do the mate-fighting bit now. Uh, not the biting part."

I shoved my way by startled pedestrians, and Noah apologized as it followed. Several Venlil stared at the human chasing a rescue; we were creating quite a spectacle. Risking a glance over my shoulder, I saw sweat beads on its skin. The burning of its legs affected it less than me, though.

The predator was close on my heels, and outrunning it seemed a physical impossibility. I waited until right when its shadow dropped to a lunging stance, before doubling back. Noah tripped over itself, as I slithered between its lanky legs. The alien found its footing, and reversed its direction.

I'd managed to put a few paces between us again, but I hadn't figured out my final act of defiance. Glim was not a number; Noah had been right, ironically. It wasn't worth living as a monster's cattle in a new place. I hopped onto the stair railing, and slid down. Gravity deposited me back in the terminal.

The human didn't risk the quick descent, when the banister wasn't meant to hold its weight. It was skipping steps all the same, bounding down three at a time. Acid seared through my leg muscles, but I willed myself onward. That tireless thing hit the ground at blinding speed too.

"I wanted to tell you...about us!" Noah called. "You deserve to feel safe."

Its footsteps pounded against the concrete, and I bolted behind the stopped train's caboose. Several passengers shouted pleas and exclamations. The Krakotl I'd been talking to tried to swoop down on me, but failed to catch an air current. Tarva and Sara simply watched the madness unfold with agape expressions.

I mounted another platform, as the rumble of an incoming train greeted my ears. The vehicle's front side was visible, and I hoped that its weight would render me dead on impact. My legs stumbled, but I forced a few more steps out of them. Noah's shadow stretched over me again; I could hear its ragged pants.

Turning into the train's motion, I flung myself forward with desperate finality. My body hurtled headlong into a collision; we all knew being captured was the worse option. The human gasped in horror, and made a lunging dive with outstretched arms. It didn't want its meal to get pulverized.

Thin fingers dug into my scruff, twisting into the soft flesh. Noah skidded on its knees, and contorted its body to tug me back. Its arm was nearly wrested from the socket, but it retained its grip. My forward momentum came to an abrupt halt, and I landed with my snout inches shy of the passing tram.

Tears streamed down my face, and I slumped my head in defeat. My body flailed weakly, but Noah had no difficulty restraining me. It was a superior creature in size and strength. I yipped in panic, swinging my claws at its face. The human shrugged off my frenzied blow, which barely nicked its skin.

"Easy, easy! You're safe now, I told you." Noah's nimble digits began kneading my scruff, and it gently brought me against its chest. "We wanted to tell you everything slowly. This is my fault, and I'm sorry."

I could feel its heart hammering, and the erratic rise and fall of its chest. The predator refused to let go, as it took a moment to catch its breath. Tarva and Sara hurried over, which caused its lips to curve up. It lifted its catch to show them; I fell limp in its arms with hopelessness. The female human passed a holopad to her counterpart, while the Venlil leader gawked.

"Noah! Are you okay?" the Venlil Governor asked, with a concerned head-tilt.

Noah nodded. "Yeah. I've got Glim from here; we need a road trip. Maybe you guys could take care of Haysi?"

"Of course. Her reaction left a lot to be desired," Sara muttered.

My muscles quivered with fear, as every rumble of the predator's chest rippled into my body. Noah strolled over to the help desk, earning open stares from several Venlil. Its sinewy arms were unwavering, though it hadn't hurt me yet. I was trapped in its clutches, and I knew its 'road trip' was to a slaughterhouse.

Noah poked my neck with its nails. "Brighten up, Glim! Looks like the train to Celgel Falls arrives any minute. You were getting on the wrong one."

I was speechless, but my chest shook with a despairing sob. The human stared with its binocular pupils, and its eyebrows pressed together. It wasn't clear why the predator kept trying to engage me. Both of us knew the truth of this encounter.

"Your Aunt Thima moved to Celgel a year ago, according to our records. You want to see her, right?" Noah pressed.

My ears perked slightly. "T-t-t...th...Thima?"

"Yeah! A nice family reunion. I'm going to tag along to make sure you don't hurt yourself, any other Venlil, or some poor Gaian out for a stroll."

"H-human. N-not...Gaian."

"No, Gaian wasn't a lie. We have lots of names, Glim: Terran, human, Earthling, mankind, and Gaian. Gaian is just one of the lesser-known ones. Call us whatever you like...not predator, I hope."

The predator delicately extended my wrist, and pressed the holopad it obtained from Sara against my claws. When I didn't snatch the device away, Noah physically bent my toes around it. The Terran released its own grip on the electronic, after checking for several seconds that I wouldn't drop it.

"It's yours. Examine the facts for yourself," the beast growled. "First contact, the peer-reviewed human empathy tests, my speech to the Federation, and our rescue of the cradle from the Arxur. That's where I'd ask you to start."

I eyed the device. "W-what?"

"You can see everything about us: the good, the bad, and the ugly. Our modern culture, our evolution and aggression, the extent of the Federation's lies, how we grow meat in lab vats rather than hunting. Some of it might shock or scare you, but it's all the truth."

"M-monster. P-predator."

"I'm sorry you feel that way. Listen, after you spend awhile with your family, I'm taking you back to the facility."

"NO! NOT C-CATTLE!"

The Venlil screaming at the top of his lungs attracted more attention, and Noah blinked in frustration. I could sense the predator's patience waning, so I hushed myself to avoid its ire. Perhaps these lies were kinder than the Arxur's torment and degradation. Humans were different in that regard.

The alien beast heaved a sigh. "You need treatment. But if you never want to see a human again, just say so once we get back. You will never hear from me or any Terran volunteers again; not inside those walls."

"I...w-want...never," I croaked.

"Okay. It's your choice. I'm just asking you to research honestly first. You can lock in your decision when we're back, and ask me anything you like on the ride."

Noah boarded the arriving train with caution, while I was still trapped in its arms. The holopad beckoned to me, as a hint of curiosity crept in. The words 'human empathy' typed themselves, without conscious effort. It was an absurd notion, but I was interested to discover what supposed evidence existed.

Playing along with the Gaians' game was harmless. A predator's kindness couldn't be that convincing, after all.

⋯ ✧ ⋯ ✧ ⋯

Chapter 87
Memory transcription subject:

Glim,
Venlil Rescue

Date [standardized human time]:
December 1, 2136

half-day train journey kickstarted my confinement with the human. The more time passed, the less I was convinced that we were in Celgel Falls to see Aunt Thima. We stopped off at a hotel for rest, until the Venlil government brought us a car and a driver. It was clear Noah had our authorities at its beck and call.

I was impressed with how well the Gaian could control its instincts, and with how thorough its propaganda was. Reading about secret predators within the Federation was jaw-dropping; that rattled my worldview to the core. It was lunacy for the Kolshians to think flesh-eaters could be tamed! Any credibility the Terrans had gained was their fault.

Human behavior did prove curious, especially rescue footage of the Gojids. That was negated by the fact that they invaded the cradle; Earth was the aggressor in the conflict. A lackluster excuse about Prime Minister Piri staging an assault was their cover for their warmongering. It was an opportunity to conquer the lesser races, and begin an empire.

But as a former exterminator, I couldn’t say I didn’t feel a sliver of doubt. Gaians broke a lot of rules that I’d known since birth, whether they were lying or not. I hadn’t worked up the courage to ask Noah any questions yet. However, there were a lot of answers I wanted to hear, when the beast was forced to cook up spontaneous retorts.

Maybe I’m not in imminent danger of being devoured. Unless we’re going to a slaughterhouse.

“…giving Haysi space. She hasn’t been eating or drinking, and I think Sara visiting would be a trigger,” Tarva was speaking to Noah, through a video call.

human pursed its lips. “We should give Haysi as much time as she needs. If she’s not even voicing her concerns, she’s not ready. Glim is trouble, but at least his mind is still there.”

“Just be careful, Noah. This isn’t the capital; it’s a rural area, where Venlil aren’t as open-minded. They don’t regularly interact with humans. You’re not exactly incognito either.”

“Are you worried about me? A monstrous predator like me can scare off a few fanatics.”

“Please, try not to scare anyone! The footage of you chasing Glim is making the rounds, and let’s just say…it’s a bad look. ‘Human ambassador hunts Venlil cattle in train station.’”

“It wasn’t like that! Glim could’ve hurt someone. I had to stop him.”

“I know, Noah. I like to be involved with things myself, but maybe we shouldn’t have gotten wrapped up in this at all. We’re too high profile to be ordinary helpers.”

Gaian scowled. “It was your idea to sponsor a Venlil in the first place. You said it was good PR to ‘do our part.’”

“And you said you wanted to. Does it really matter whose fault it is?” Governor Tarva hissed.

“No. I just don’t want your media team to toss me under the bus.”

“Stars, I hate all of your idioms. ‘Kill two birds with one stone.’ ‘Cut to the chase.’ ‘Stabbed in the back.’ Are there any that aren’t about being maimed or killed?”

“One or two.”

“You’re infuriating. We’ll settle this later. Just be safe, okay?”

Noah bared its teeth to itself, as the Venlil leader abandoned the call. I studied the Gaian for a long moment, and considered the adoration in Tarva’s eyes. That emotion looked like love, but I didn’t understand how such strong feelings could arise toward a monster. Perhaps I should regard the beast with gendered pronouns, like he was a person.

Earth’s presence was less nefarious than Wriss’s Dominion, from what I could tell. The empathy tests were convincing, since it was difficult to fool scientists on a neurochemical level. Why had Noah lied to us though? His actions hadn’t been innocuous, conning and misleading us.

Gaian ambassador was ignoring my presence, for now; I was certain he was avoiding direct eye contact. His focus drifted to a sign in the distance, which read ‘Celgel Retirement Home.’ His hand reached for a visor, and he pressed it across his paralyzing pupils. I wondered what that accomplished, when every Venlil here knew of his predatory identity.

“W-why do you w-wear your visor out here?” I gasped out.

human palmed his chin. “Because, these are elderly Venlil. I don’t want to give anyone a heart attack. Any Venlil over 65 weren’t allowed in the exchange program, to avoid cardiac episodes.”

“T-thima…is how old? I don’t know h-how many…years—”

“She’s 74, Glim. You were gone for 11 years.”

“No…that’s not p-possible.”

“I’m sorry. I hate to spring this on you, but your aunt’s memory is fading. She’s in the late stages of dementia.”

My gaze shifted to the rural landscape, which stretched to the horizon opposite the assisted living facility. A family reunion where Thima forgot me hadn’t been in my imaginings. I was saddened that I hadn’t been there to help, and to visit her. Had her mind deteriorated because she was alone?

Noah hesitated, before moving a hand slowly. His fingers hovered over my wrist for several seconds, giving me a chance to pull away. The Gaian empathetically squeezed my forearm, like a Venlil would with their tail; his touch was delicate and frail. It was clear he was leaving the option for me to withdraw, since I knew from the train station that he was much stronger.

re were several things I’d read that weighed on my mind; I couldn’t succumb to believing the narrative. The humans were allies with the child-eating Arxur, even if they’d used that alignment to liberate Venlil captives. Their current objective was unraveling the Federation, and they were bestial hunters too. Apparently, Terran aggression had been documented by observers, prior to first contact.

I can’t remember learning about them in school, other than vaguely as an extinct predator race, I mused. The internet claims they’ve had over 10,000 battles in their history.

“H-hundreds of wars in just the century…after your w-world war. The first one,” I whined. “How c-could you ever…k-keep peace?”

Noah was quiet for several seconds. “We have to grow the fuck up. Humans want peace, yet we’ve only ever known competition. It doesn’t come naturally, but we’re starting to act like a united planet.”

“V-venlil, always…at peace.”

“I doubt that. The Kolshian gentling took hold, and the Farsul sanitized your past. I think you used to be feisty herbivores, until they convinced you of your weakness.”

“And…if we’re n-not s-strong?”

“We’ll teach you. We’ll protect you, with a fierceness you’ve never seen before.”

Noah’s lips curved up, and I dissociated myself from the rush of fear. Perhaps the constant snarling betrayed his deceit, since the gesture came off as subconscious. The human rushed to cover his mouth, like he knew he’d done something wrong. If threat displays were intuitive, that explained the full-face masks at the hospital.

I recalled how the Arxur would snarl just looking at us, licking their lips with appetite. Sapient predators used their teeth to assert dominance in conversation too, from what I could tell. The guards would flash fangs when contesting a particular catch, or boasting of their hunts. The Gaians possessed the same urges.

Venlil driver parked the car outside the nursing home, and Noah opened the door. I felt paralyzed, befuddled by the paradoxical humans. It wasn’t clear what to think of them. Their motives were ambiguous, and their mannerisms flipped between hostility and sympathy on a dime.

“Smiling, or ‘snarling’ as you say, is a submissive gesture in primates. I understand it is not so for other animals,” Noah sighed.

I coaxed myself out of the car. “N-nonsense. H-how can t-teeth…baring…”

“Be friendly? It’s about their position. Teeth apart, jaw tension, and lips curled back; that’s actual hostility. But teeth together and lips relaxed shows we’re not about to attack.”

“S-so it’s saying you don’t want to bite?”

And predators need to communicate that constantly?!

Gaian ambassador nodded. “Exactly. Venlil don’t understand the subtle difference. The few that try to replicate it usually just look constipated, man.”

I chuckled, in spite of myself. “You h-have these…answers well-rehearsed.”

“I’m used to explaining everything we do. If I’d explained us better in my speech, a billion people wouldn’t have died. Since then, I sifted through our evolution pretty thoroughly.”

Noah’s voice turned scratchy, and his ensuing cough sounded a bit congested. Did the Gaian consider himself responsible for the extermination attempt? He’d stated Earth’s case pretty well, for five minutes broken up by hecklers; guns had been trained on him the whole time too. A non-predator would’ve frozen in fear.

fact that he gave anyone pause, over exterminating warlike horrors, is miraculous. Nobody in his position could’ve done better.

human pawed at his nose, before opening the door to the lobby. He gagged at once, and muttered something about “disinfectant smell.” A middle-aged Venlil sat at a reception desk, startling at our appearance. Her eyes went wide with fear, and her ears pinned back. She snapped out of it enough to tap a notice with her tail.

A sign was taped to the desk, reading “No Humans Permitted” in several scripts. The Gaian crossed his arms, and leaned back with an intimidating frown. I observed the tightness of his jaw and the slant of his eyebrows; this was genuine hostility. It was worryingly easy to decipher the predator’s mouth contortions, once told what to look for.

Noah sighed. “See, Glim? Still think we run the show here?”

“I don’t know. You put up with a lot,” I muttered.

“W-what…you c-can’t be here,” the Venlil receptionist stammered. “You need to leave! T-the human, anyway.”

Gaian lifted his visor. “I think you’ll make an exception for the Terran ambassador. I have powerful friends.”

“There’s s-security footage! Are you g-going…going to attack us to get t-through? You’re trespassing.”

“Glim wants to visit his Aunt Thima. Make that happen, and we’ll leave.”

“N-no. You’re not welcome here, Noah.”

veins in the Gaian’s neck bulged, and his fingers clenched tighter. His lips curled back to his pink gums, while his eyes dilated. So that was what a primate’s aggressive snarl looked like. I skittered back, remembering Noah’s warning about intent to bite. I didn’t want to be within snacking distance.

My inner exterminator agreed that humans shouldn’t be prowling our streets, and wished for their non-existence. But my sentimental side remembered Noah tucking me in, and playing games with Haysi and I. If the predator was emulating empathy, he deserved an award. There was more to this conqueror than my Arxur tormentors.

Venlil receptionist wasn’t backing down from her statement, and was gaining more confidence by the second. She bared her own teeth, reaching for a phone. Perhaps this employee intended to dial exterminators. I was increasingly worried about the Gaian biting this individual.

“Don’t talk to Noah like that!” A Zurulian nurse trotted into the room, and glared at the receptionist. “Please, forgive Carliva; she doesn’t think highly of your kind.”

“Those flesh-beasts drain our resources, and our taxes go to their meat factories! They set up their encampments anywhere, and litter our big cities. Some of them don’t even work!” the Venlil snapped back.

“Earth got bombed to oblivion. Those humans lost family members and everything they own. Wouldn’t you be grieving too?”

quadruped flicked her ears, and Carliva slunk off with a look of loathing. The Zurulian nurse shook her head, before approaching Noah with cautious steps. The Gaian refitted his visor, and clasped his hands behind his back. He dipped his head, perhaps to show appreciation.

“Please listen, Ambassador Noah. I can’t allow you to interact with our patients,” the nurse said.

Noah hissed in exasperation. “What?! I thought you were on my side!”

“I am. Many of our residents have memory problems, and wouldn’t know what a human is. A scare at their advanced age could be deadly. You don’t want to kill someone, do you?”

“Of course not. But Glim’s been an Arxur captive for a decade. He needs to see his Aunt Thima.”

“Why don’t I take Glim to her room, and you wait here? Then you leave after, without any unwanted incidents.”

predator paced for a few seconds, startling the Zurulian. Even with the visor on, I could sense his unnatural eyes on me. Noah was considering whether I’d run off at the first opportunity, which was a high possibility. He must be feigning deliberation to seem reasonable. Why would he let me out of his sight?

human went to great lengths to track my escape, and hunted me in a public venue. He wouldn’t release his catch.

“Okay. Thanks for helping us, Nurse.” The Gaian sat in a chair, which was comically small for him. “I trust you, Glim. The question is if you trust me.”

I withheld a disbelieving hiss, and tried to make sense of my sudden release. Of course I didn’t trust a predator, after years as a cattle captive! Besides, his introduction started with deceit, which eliminated any chance of mutual trust. Concealing all information about his kind didn’t inspire positive thoughts.

Noah had done an admirable job of swaying me, when I scorned any nuance originally. But our first encounter proved he was a trickster. I followed the Zurulian down a hallway, and relaxed as the Gaian didn’t follow us. This was a pristine opportunity to escape captivity; I could evade detection better in this less-integrated town.

Zurulian stopped outside one door, and gestured for me to enter. My ears perked up with hope, as I crept into the room. Thima wheezed on her side, and her facial fur was starkly snow white. The glassiness in her eyes reminded me of cattle Venlil; drool was running down her chin. An old sitcom played on a TV, which she blankly watched.

“Thima?” I whispered.

My aunt screeched. “HELP! There’s a s-strange man in my room!”

“It’s me, Glim. I came to visit you.”

“You’re not Glim. Glim was captured by the Arxur.”

“Y-yes, that was true for 11 years. The humans traded for me. See the neck brand?”

“Human? What kind of species name is that?”

“The aliens, Thima…the predators. They returned me, your nephew.”

“Lies! I want you gone. You’re not Glim!”

“S-stop playing. Don’t you recognize my voice?”

Aunt Thima glowered at me, before wailing for assistance. She began unplugging the wires from her arms in a fit, and knocked her drinking water from the nightstand. I gaped in horror, as the one person who loved me wanted me gone. Tears swelled in my eyes, and I rushed out of the room.

Zurulian medic yelled at me to calm down, but my feet were moving on their own. I was blind to my direction and my surroundings; the facility was a blur. There was nothing left here on Venlil Prime, not even my family. The world had changed too much to process. All I wanted was for Thima to hold me, and whisper that it was alright.

My paws wrapped around something warm, and I clung on for dear life. Sobs rattled my body, so I pressed my face into a synthetic fabric. My hugging support tensed beneath my arms, and fleshy appendages tapped my back. I let go with horror, as I realized where I‘d run. My instincts went back to the predator for comfort.

Noah massaged my neck. “Shhh. It’s okay. You’re okay.”

“You don’t know what it’s like!” I screamed.

“Actually, I do. My dad had Alzheimer’s. I’d visit him every weekend, and he didn’t remember who I was. He’d tell me about his little boy, Noah, who wanted to be an astronaut…and I’d just smile.”

“But I…needed T-Thima. Take me back to the facility! Take me back. Anywhere but here.”

“I know it’s hard, but it’s not her fault. Are you sure you want to leave?”

“Please, get me out of here. I can’t lose anyone else. That’s not Thima anymore.”

“You don't mean that. Sometimes, she remembers and she’s there, Glim. Tarva’s people got her to record those messages for you. She was glad you’re home.”

Gaian picked me up, a stoic expression on his face. My profession had always taught me that predators should be eradicated, but this was the nicest hunter I’d ever encountered. For some reason, my subconscious felt bonded to Noah. He was a steady presence, when everything else was crumbling.

I couldn’t ignore the evidence from our travels either. The way the Venlil receptionist spoke to my caretaker was irreverent and hostile. Judging from Tarva’s phone call, it sounded like open criticism was allowed on the internet too. Those attitudes wouldn’t be allowed to circulate, if humans conquered our home.

Furthermore, the oblivious Gaians at lunch had been discussing morals and sympathy. They had no way of knowing anyone was listening. With my exposure to the Arxur, I knew how different those pitying attitudes were. The grays considered keeping us as prey to be our rightful state, and they flaunted it.

“Glim, can you talk to Haysi?” Noah slid back into the car, and removed his visor. “You could help us explain it to the other refugees, better than we did for you.”

Tears dripped down my cheeks. “I don’t know. M-maybe.”

“Okay. And do you still want me to drop contact with you, when we get back?”

Gaian stiffened, sucking in a sharp breath. It was as if the ambassador was bracing himself for rejection; that implied it would cause him pain if I answered in the negative. Noah’s body language betrayed that he cared what I thought of him. The torrent of fear since first contact seemed to have taken its toll.

“I don’t think that will be necessary,” I croaked.

human curved his lips. “Good. I haven’t taught you the half of our body language.”

My gaze darted out the window, and a shudder crept down my spine. I, of all Venlil, shouldn’t be trusting of a lying predator, but I was giving Noah a second chance. Human charisma had swayed my feelings a bit too much.

⋯ ✧ ⋯ ✧ ⋯